<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bright morning starre: or, The resolution and exposition of the 22. Psalme preached publikely in foure sermons at Lincolne. By John Smith preacher of the citie.</title>
            <author>Smyth, John, d. 1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113474</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848708</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1693:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bright morning starre: or, The resolution and exposition of the 22. Psalme preached publikely in foure sermons at Lincolne. By John Smith preacher of the citie.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, John, d. 1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 196 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, Printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge. And are to be solde at the signe of the Crowns in Pauls Churchyard [in London] by Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's address from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BRIGHT <hi>MOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING STARRE:</hi> OR, The Reſolution and <hi>Expoſition of the 22. Pſalme, preached</hi> publikely in foure ſermons <hi>at Lincolne.</hi> By <hi>IOHN SMITH Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apoc. 22.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I am the roote and the Generation of Dauid, and the Bright Morning ſtarre.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by IOHN LEGAT, <hi>Printer to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> 1603. And are to be ſolde at the ſigne of the Crowns in Pauls Churchyard by <hi>Simon Waterſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of William Wray</figDesc>
                  <p>EMMANUEL</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Chriſte Patris Will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Coll Emman. Cantab.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:2"/>
            <head>To THE RIGHT Worſhipfull, religious, and <hi>courteous Knight, Sir</hi> William Wray, my approoued good <hi>friend and benefactor,</hi> ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the Lord <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIr: it ſeemeth a thing very reaſonable to me, that ſeeing euery bald tale, vaine enterlude, and pelting ballad, hath the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of the Preſſe, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and readings of miniſters may challenge the ſame: the worlde is full of <hi>Guy</hi> of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, <hi>William</hi> of Cloudeſlee, <hi>Skoggins,</hi> and <hi>Wolners</hi> ieſts, and writings of like qualitie: and therein men take great delight to read, and ſo make themſelues merrie with other mens ſinnes, beſtowing to this purpoſe much
<pb facs="tcp:13820:3"/>vaine time and ſuperfluous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences: and J thinke the Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhop, and ſome mens ſhelues are better furniſhed with ſuch trifles, which deceiue the minde and affection as the baite doeth the fiſh, then with wholeſome writings of nature, arte, or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. In which reſpect in ſeemeth to haue beene leſſe hurtfull to mankind, if Printing had neuer beene inuented, ſauing that the vſe of a thing is not to be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den becauſe of the abuſe: theſe things conſidered, haue imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to publiſh my meditations and readings to the worlds views and ſeeing that Printing is a trade wherby diuers good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians maintaine their charge, &amp; that for want of better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ſometime are compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to proſtitute their Preſſes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s and vanitie: ſeeing alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:13820:3"/>trueth may better appeare by writings of diuers men, which perhaps one or two or more could not readily diſcouer: therefore I haue thought good in ſome part to preuent the danger of the one, and promote the benefit of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. J haue not varniſhed my writing with the ſuperficiall learning of words, and figures, tongues, and teſtimonies of men (which not withſtanding I do not diſalow) but becauſe I purpoſed to apply my ſtyle to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſimple, I indeauour to vtter matter with all plaineneſſe of wordes and ſentences. Nowe becauſe I haue experienced your ſelfe to be vnder the Kings Maiestie a principall profeſſor and protectour of religion in theſe quarters: (for what a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of faithfull miniſters are debters to you in the fleſh?) and
<pb facs="tcp:13820:4"/>for that I among the reſt haue reſted vnder your ſhaddowe, your name came firſt to my mind in this writing: wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you vouchſafe to intitle it with your name, and I ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe graced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. The Lord increaſe in your ſelfe and your vertuous Lady and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all manner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces &amp; bleſſings.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſh. humbly in all manner of Chriſtian affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iohn Smith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13820:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The reſolution of</hi> of the 22. Pſalme, which may be <hi>intituled the</hi> Bright Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Starre.</head>
            <p>THe time when this Pſalme was penned is vnknowne in ſpeciall: generally notwithſtanding it may ſeeme to be, when the Prophet was in ſome great conflict of conſcience, and temptation to deſpaire, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he gathering conſolation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth at the length.</p>
            <p>The Argument of the Pſalme is a diſcription of the eſtate of euery true Chriſtian and godly heart in the perſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13820:5"/>of Dauid: alſo a type of the ſufferings &amp; glory of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The pſalme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth two partes:</p>
            <list>
               <item>The title or inſcription.</item>
               <item>The matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The title contayneth foure particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The manner of writing, which is in forme of <hi>a Pſalme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The perſon that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it, who was Dauid.</item>
               <item>3 The perſon to whome it was committed to be kept, ſet, and ſong: who is called <hi>the maſter muſitian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 The matter and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pſalme, which is concerning the morning ſtarre.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The matter and ſubſtance of the Palme comprehendeth a: Complaint: Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13820:5"/>
            <p>The complaint contayned in the two firſt verſes hath 2. things. 1. the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whome he complayneth: <hi>(God:)</hi> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyfied by an argument of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. <hi>(my God)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The thing whereof he complayneth, which is that <hi>God hath forſaken him.</hi> Which the prophet auoucheth by 2. reaſons.</p>
            <p>The firſt, that ſeeing <hi>God did not helpe him, but was farre from his health:</hi> therfore he forſooke him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, <hi>that ſeeing God heard not the wordes of his roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nor gaue audience to his prayer:</hi> therefore he forſooke him.</p>
            <p>This praier which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet profeſſeth he made to the Lord, in the time of this his wofull deſertion hath two
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13820:6"/>adiunctes:
<list>
                  <item>1 His prayer was feruent.</item>
                  <item>2. His praier was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The feruency of his prayer hath two partes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>faith: <hi>(my God.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>deſire: <hi>(roaring crye.)</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The continuance of his prayer: <hi>(day and night.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the firſt part of the pſalme the complaint.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the pſalme which is the prayer followeth.</p>
            <p>The prayer hath a</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Supplication: contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo a deprecation.</item>
               <item>2 A Gratulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſupplication is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to the 22. verſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is expreſt both the faith &amp; aſſurance the prophet concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13820:6"/>to obtaine: and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: which are the two eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall partes of a feruent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>The faith of the prophet is grounded vpon 4. arguments to the 11. verſe: The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or ground of faith is in the 3. verſe taken from the nature &amp; office of God, which is to ſanctifie and redeeme the Church that he may be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; glorified by his church: concluded thus.</p>
            <p>If thou wilt ſanctifie the church and be praiſed by the church, then deliuer me the redeemer of the Church, without whoſe deliuerance, neither thy ſelf can be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor thy church redeemed or ſanctified.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſanctifie the Church <hi>(for thou art holy)</hi> &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13820:7"/>thou wilt be praiſed by the Church (<hi>for thou inhabiteſt the praiſes of Iſraell.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>deliuer me verſ. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the argument is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Chriſt: to Dauid thus.</p>
            <p>Thou Lord art holy ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying thy children: therfore ſanctifie me, and deliuer me from the power of ſinne and thy wrath, that I may praiſe thee with al the true Iſraelites, whoſe praiſes are offered vp to thee, as to the only owner and poſſeſſor thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument or ground of faith is in the 4. &amp; 5. verſes framed thus. If the fathers that truſted in thee, &amp; called vpon thee are ſaued &amp; deliuerd and were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: then ſaue me alſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13820:7"/>who am their ſauiour.</p>
            <p>But <hi>the fathers</hi> of the olde teſtament &amp;c. <hi>are ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore alſo <hi>ſaue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me verſ. 11</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is: for that Chriſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily muſt be ſaued and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, ſeeing the fathers were ſaued by vertue of his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: whereas they could not ſo haue beene, if he had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus the argument is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Chriſt: to Dauid thus.</p>
            <p>As God hath delt with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo will he deale with me.</p>
            <p>But God deliuered our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that faithfully prayed.</p>
            <p>Therefore he will deliuer me alſo that pray faithfully: &amp; ſo this argument is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13820:8"/>the experience of Gods goodnes to others.</p>
            <p>The third argument or ground of faith is in the 6.7. and 8. verſes taken from Relation of Gods mercy to mans miſery: diſpoſed thus:</p>
            <p>The moſt mercifull God wil releeue the miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calling vpon him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>But I am a moſt miſerable creature. &amp;c. and thou a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>releeue and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me. verſ. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The minour of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is amplified compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely and ſimply.</p>
            <p>The compariſon is taken from a worme. As a worme is expoſed to all wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, and of baſe account: ſo am I.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13820:8"/>
            <p>The ſimple arguments are the parts of Chriſts miſerie, which are three: 1. he was ſhamed. 2. contemned. 3. derided.</p>
            <p>He beeing God moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, was ſhamed and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by man, that is, Adam duſt and aſhes.</p>
            <p>He that ſhould haue beene accounted of, as the onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of his people, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to the people.</p>
            <p>He<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whome men ſhould haue gloried and reioyced in, was derided and mockt by all men that beheld him.</p>
            <p>Chriſt was mockt by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and ſpeech.</p>
            <p>The mocking geſtures are two, mowing &amp; wrying the mouth: &amp; nodding the head.</p>
            <p>The skoffing ſpeech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth an ironical co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarietie:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13820:9"/>for they ſay one thing that mocke Chriſt, and meane the cleane contrarie: thus they ſpeake,</p>
            <p>God will deliuer him that he loueth, and that truſteth in God.</p>
            <p>But he is beloued of God, &amp; truſteth in God: <hi>ergo</hi> God will ſaue him.</p>
            <p>But their meaning is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to this ſpeech: which is this.</p>
            <p>God will deliuer him that he loueth, and that truſteth in him:</p>
            <p>But God doeth not deliuer him: <hi>ergo,</hi> he neither is loued of God, nor truſteth in God.</p>
            <p>Thus the third argument is applied to Chriſt: to Dauid alſo in the ſame ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth argument or ground of faith is in the 9. and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13820:9"/>10. verſes, taken from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Gods goodneſſe to himſelf in time paſt, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thus:</p>
            <p>As thou haſt dealt with me before, ſo deale with me nowe.</p>
            <p>But thou haſt hitherto preſerued and deliuered me: <hi>ergo</hi> doe ſo nowe.</p>
            <p>The minor of the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is amplified by a diſtribution or enumeration of parts, thus: thou haſt preſerued me in my life, birth, and conception.</p>
            <p>Thus the fourth argument is applied to Chriſt: and in the ſame ſenſe alſo to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Prophet hath vttered his faith, which is the firſt eſſentiall part of his praier: his deſire which is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d eſſential part followeth.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13820:10"/>
            <p>The deſire of the Prophet is expreſt in the 11. verſe: <hi>[Be not farre from me]</hi> and vrged by a reaſon, <hi>à relatis paribus,</hi> thus:</p>
            <p>If helpe be farre off, then thou wilt be neere to help thy ſeruants.</p>
            <p>But helpe is farre off: <hi>ergo</hi> be neere to helpe. Or thus:</p>
            <p>Thou wilt helpe the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and helpeleſſe:</p>
            <p>But I am afflicted and helpeleſſe: <hi>ergo</hi> helpe me.</p>
            <p>Nowe furthermore, both the Prophets deſire and this reaſon whereupon it is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced are handled by inuerſion of methode, for firſt the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is handled, then the deſire.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is handled to the 19. verſe, where the deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and extreame miſerie of the Prophet is propounded in 2
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13820:10"/>kinds: Firſt that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and immediately ſeazed vpon his ſoule, which by ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathie onely affected his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. verſ. 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, that which direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly ſeazed vpon his bodie, and by compaſſion onely affected his ſenſitiue facultie. verſ. 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>The proper affliction of his ſoule is deliuered in three arguments, <hi>viz.</hi> the cauſe, the adiunct, and the effect.</p>
            <p>The cauſes are the deuill and his angels, allegorically figured vnder the names of Bulls and Lyons.</p>
            <p>Theſe deuils are of two conditions: ſome miniſters &amp; ſeruants to their maſter the principall: other the cheife or maſter deuill.</p>
            <p>The miniſtring deuils co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13820:11"/>are allegorized vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tearmes of Bulls, as beeing creatures inferiour in ſtrength and rage to the lyon the king of the beaſts of the forreſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe deuilliſh Buls are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by their qualities and effects: their qualities are 3: young, fatte, ſtrong, verſ. 12.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Young: <hi>vz.</hi> ſuch as are not cicured or tamed, but are without the yoke, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Belial: not ſubiect to any order.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Fatte and large limmed. ſuch as were bred in Baſhan, where was the largeſt breed, and the fatteſt fed cattel, Deu. 32.14. which inſinuateth the inſolencie, arrogancy, &amp; pride of theſe deuils.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Strong and mightie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing principalities &amp; powers, as the Apoſtle tearmeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13820:11"/>Eph. 6.12. preuailing againſt the world of the vngodly.</p>
            <p>Theſe are their qualities: their effects are two, verſ. 12.13.</p>
            <p>Firſt they incloſe him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with terror and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly they gape vpon him with their mouths readie to ſwallowe him vp body and ſoule; the bodie in the graue or corruption: the ſoule in deſpaire and helliſh torments, as much as in them reſteth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are one ſort of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills, that miniſter: the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and Arch-deuill euen Beelzebub the prince of the deuils is termed a ramping &amp; roaring lyon. verſ. 13.</p>
            <p>A lyon, as the king of all the helliſh fiendes to whome they voluntarily become ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13820:12"/>
            <p>Roaring, as now ready to deuour the pray (for ſo is the vſe of lyons Amos. 3.4. to roare when they are vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pray.)</p>
            <p>Ramping, that is hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitten and ſo moſt eagerly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent vpon the pray, as the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were kept faſting for the deuouring of Daniell. Theſe are the cauſes of Chriſts afflictions vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly. The adiunct &amp; effects follow.</p>
            <p>The adiunct is the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his miſery vttered by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon to water ſpilt vpon the ground, which cannot be gathered vp againe, euen ſo (ſaith the prophet) my miſery is irrecouerable. v. 14.</p>
            <p>The effects are in number fiue:</p>
            <p>Firſt effect is the diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13820:12"/>of the Animall facultie, which is by this miſery interrupted: verſe. 14. the ſinewes, liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, brawnes, &amp; tendons, which are the inſtruments of ſenſe and motion beeing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by the animall facultie of the ſoule, and ſo the bones which are as it were the ſtuds of the bodie were laxed and vntied (for the diſioyning of the bones is expreſt, ver. 17.)</p>
            <p>Second effect: that <hi>his heart which</hi> (as anatomie teacheth) <hi>is in the middeſt of the bowells, was melted like waxe:</hi> that is the vitall facultie was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: whoſe principall ſeate is in the heart, from whence vitall ſpirits by the arteries, whoſe originall is the heart, are diffuſed to euery liuing part. This vitall facultie was molten and quailed ſo as the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13820:13"/>ſoule ceaſed the execution thereof for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Third effect: that <hi>his ſtrength was dryed vp like a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheard</hi> that is, the <hi>humidum radicale</hi> or naturall moiſture which is the oile to the lampe of life beeing the foundation of our ſtrengh and vigor, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and ſpent, and ſo the naturall facultie decayed, ther being not much more moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in the partes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die then in a potſheard ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the ouen.</p>
            <p>Fourth effect: that <hi>his tong claue to his lawes,</hi> he being ſcarſe able through the fierce aſſaultes of Gods wrath to moue his tongue: ſo that here probably may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectured that the faculty of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe inſtrument is the tongue, was ſuſpended: though we denie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13820:13"/>not but alſo by this phraſe the prophet may ſignifie his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate drought.</p>
            <p>Theſe foure are the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all effectes of the torment which now he ſuffered, now followeth one generall effect, <hi>vz.</hi> that he was brought <hi>into the duſt of death,</hi> that is, vnto the graue. verſe. 1.5. but this effect is ſolitarily here attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the Lord, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted from the former cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: for the prophet by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtrophe, turneth his ſpeech vnto the Lord: ſaying. <hi>Thou haſt brought me.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is the affliction which immediately ſeazed vpon his ſoule, yet by ſimpathy alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bodie, by theſe effects,</p>
            <p>Now the affliction which entred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bodie priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by compaſſion vpon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13820:14"/>his ſoule follow: where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo: the cauſes, &amp; practiſe thereof. The cauſes are the wicked, Iewes and Gentiles which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpired and procured his death, who are called dogs according to the cuſtome of the ſcripture and expounded to be the wicked. v. 16.</p>
            <p>The parts of this affliction are fiue.</p>
            <p>Firſt the wicked incloſe him, that is whippe him, ſpitte vpon him, ſmite him with fiſt and rod, crowne him with thornes, and ſuch like men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the goſpell (for here the ſigne is put for the thing ſignified, it being the cuſtome of the people to ſlocke about the perſon vpon whome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution is done.) verſe. 16.</p>
            <p>Secondly they pierced or digged his hands and feet,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13820:14"/>when they nayled him to the croſſe, which inſinuateth the great woundes that were mad in his hands and feet, as if they had beene digged with the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes or paues of a lyon, as the old tranſlatour hath it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corrupt hebrue word. v. 16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly they wrack him, &amp; diſioynt all his boanes, ſo as they may be nombred, and diſcerned ſeuerally each from other, as is cuſtomable to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are wracked: here is <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num pro ſignato:</hi> v. 17.</p>
            <p>Fourthly they behold and looke vpon him without pity and compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yea they mock and ſcoffe at him with taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bitter ſloutes, and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpeech, here is leſſe ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and men ſignified: <hi>ſignum pro ſignato.</hi> v. 17.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13820:15"/>
            <p>Laſtly they take from him his garmentes and ſtrip him na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: a vild indignity: now his garments appertayned (as it is in vſe with vs) to the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who were the ſouldiers: they therefore firſt deuide his vnder garments and euery one taketh, his part: but his vpper garment beeing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeame is not deuided or cut in pieces, but for it they caſt loues to whome it ſhall appertaine: and falling to one the other loſt their partes. v. 18.</p>
            <p>This is the affliction that immediately ſeazed vpon his body, but compaſſiuely alſo vpon his ſoule:</p>
            <p>Thus the reaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming the prophetes deſire is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13820:15"/>deſire which is handled alſo v. 19.20.21. wherein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider foure particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whome he offereth this his deſire, which is the Lord, whome he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuleth <hi>his ſtrength,</hi> becauſe he miniſtred vnto him ſtrength to beare all that was laid vpon him.</p>
            <p>Second: the thing he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for, expreſt in diuers phrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>(be not farre of: haſten to helpe, deliuer, ſaue, anſwer.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Third: the perſon for whome he prayeth expreſt thus: <hi>me, my ſoule, my deſolate one.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Fourth: the euill fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he deſireth deliuerance: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt diuerſly: <hi>from the ſword, from the power of the dogge, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyons mouth, from the hornes of the vnicornes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13820:16"/>
            <p>Thus the prophets deſire or requeſt is handled: and ſo the ſupplication.</p>
            <p>The gratulation or thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, which is the ſecond part of the prayer followeth.</p>
            <p>This thankfulnes is 1. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: 2. propheſied.</p>
            <p>It is promiſed to the 26. verſe:</p>
            <p>This promiſe of thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is propounded and then repeated and concluded. It is propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; handled to the 25. verſe, and that in the parts, or ſignes, or declarations of thankefulnes which are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Signe of thankefullnes: is Confeſſion, which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring of Gods (name or) attributes, as his mercy, and iuſtice &amp;c. to the members of the Church which are Chriſts brethren according to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13820:16"/>fleſh Heb. 2.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Signe of thankefullnes: is a commendation of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of theſe attributes to the honour and praiſe of God &amp; that <hi>in the open aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Signe of thankefullnes: is the Inciting and prouoking of them that feare God, the <hi>ſeed of Iacob and Iſrael: to praiſe and magnifie &amp; feare the Lord:</hi> to be a meanes to bring others to god alſo.</p>
            <p>Theſe three parts or ſignes of thankefullneſſe are amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a reaſon, enforcing the performance of the promiſe made before: which reaſon is taken <hi>â paribus.</hi> &amp; is ſet downe Negatiuely and Affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Negatiuely in 3. phraſes: he hath not 1. <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> 2. <hi>abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> 3. <hi>hid his face from the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13820:17"/>of the poore. ergo:</hi> thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt be performed.</p>
            <p>Affirmatiuely: <hi>he heard when the poore and humbled in ſpirit praied:</hi> and therefore thankefulneſſe muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>Thus the promiſes of thankfulneſſe is propounded &amp; handled: It is alſo repeated verſ. 25. and that in two parts thereof before handled, v. 22. The one part of thankefulnes, praiſe, and commendation of God is further enlarged by the circumſtance of the place: <hi>the great congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other part of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, Confeſſion is expreſt in a newe phraſe <hi>[paying of the vowes]</hi> which were voluntarie ſacrifices.</p>
            <p>Thus thankefulneſſe is promiſed.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13820:17"/>
            <p>Thankefulnes alſo is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied to the ende of the Pſalme: which ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the ſubiects of Chriſts kingdome, who are in the ſequele of the pſalme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and diſtributed into their ſeuerall kinds.</p>
            <p>Firſt they are deſcribed by 6. arguments in the 26. verſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Adiunct: <hi>the poore,</hi> that is, ſuch as are poore in ſpirit, Mat. 5.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Is an effect: <hi>ſhal eate,</hi> that is, beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt. Ioh. 6.35.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Adiunct: <hi>ſhall be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that is, ſhall haue peace &amp; ioy ſpirituall, Mat. 5.6. Ioh. 7.38.</p>
            <p n="4">Is an effect: <hi>ſhall ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord,</hi> that is, ſhall care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſe the meanes of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby God is ſought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13820:18"/>and found, Mat. 7.7.</p>
            <p n="5">5 An effect: <hi>ſhall praiſe the Lord</hi> by a godly life, and with heart and voice ſinging Pſalmes of praiſe: Math, 5.16. Coloſſ. 3.16.</p>
            <p n="6">6 An adiunct: <hi>your heart ſhall liue for euer;</hi> which is life euerlaſting the reward of all the former. Iohn. 4.14.</p>
            <p>Thus the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of whome thankfullnes is propheſied are deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Furthermore the perſon of whome thankfullnes is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyed, namely the members of Chriſt, and Subiects of his kingdome, are diſtributed into their ſeverall ſorts and kindes, thus:</p>
            <p>Perſons propheſied to be thankefull are,</p>
            <p>Parents and progenitors.</p>
            <p>Children and poſteritie.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13820:18"/>
            <p>Perents (&amp; ſo conſequently children) are diſtinguiſhed by two adiuncts:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Is their nation: they ſhal be Gentiles and not onely Iewes.</item>
               <item>2 Is their condition: they ſhall be of the poorer ſort, as well as of the rich.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Gentiles are deſcribed both by the parts and cauſe of their thankefulneſſe: the parts of the thankefulneſſe of the Gentiles are three. v. 27.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They ſhall remember themſelues, and take notice of their ſinnefull and accurſed eſtate, and ſo humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They ſhall turne vnto the Lord forſaking their idols and other ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 They ſhall worſhip the Lord in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13820:19"/>
            <p>The cauſe of the Gentiles thankefulneſſe is expreſt, v. 28. where there is the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an obiection which might thus be made by a Iew.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Shall the Gentiles alſo become ſubiects of the kingdom of the Meſſias, who were ſometime execrable?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> There is nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to God: for ſeeing he is king, and ſo ruleth among the heathen, he is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the Gentiles alſo, and of ſtones to raiſe vp children to Abraham.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt diſtinction of the perſons by their natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The ſecond diſtinction is, that poore and rich alſo ſhall be thankefull: and that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. v. 29.</p>
            <p>The rich who are called the fat men of the earth haue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13820:19"/>their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>eating, &amp; worſhipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poore or afflicted perſons are of two ſortes,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Such as goe downe into the duſt,</hi> that is beggars and baſſe perſons.</item>
               <item>2 Such <hi>as cannot quicken their owne ſoule,</hi> that is perſons condemned to die, or perſons ſick of deadly diſeaſes &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All theſe afflicted perſons haue their thankfull actions aſſigned them, which is that they ſhall <hi>bow before him: (ſignum pro ſignato, Metony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia)</hi> namely they ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him.</p>
            <p>Thus the parentes which are the firſt ſort of perſons with their thankfull actions, are propounded.</p>
            <p>The children and poſteritie alſo haue their thankful actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof aſſigned:</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13820:20"/>
            <p>The thankfull actions of the poſteritie are two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 They ſhall ſerue the lord in the obedience of his lawe, which is ſet out by the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, (<hi>for euer they ſhall be reckened to him.</hi> verſe 30.</item>
               <item n="2">2 Action of thankfulneſſe is that when they are come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church by effectuall vocation, <hi>they ſhall declare his righteouſnes;</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The reaſon of theſe thankfull actions of the poſteritie of the gentiles is for that God hath <hi>wrought righteouſnes for a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be borne,</hi> that is either for their poſteritie, or ſome other ſtraung people that as yet are vnborne by ſpirituall regeneration.</p>
            <p>This thankfulnes is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied: and ſo the whole
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13820:20"/>pſalme is reſolued.</p>
            <p>In the Complaint and the Supplication Chriſts prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is deſcribed both in his ſacrifice and interceſſion.</p>
            <p>In the promiſe of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, Chriſts propheſie is compriſed.</p>
            <p>In the propheſie of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe Chriſts kingdome is comprehended.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13820:21"/>
            <head>ANNOTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and obſeruations out of <hi>the 22. Pſalme.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the Title of the Pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Pſalme:</note> THis Pſalme containeth a pittifull complaint, a feruent praier, a promiſe and propheſie of thankefulneſſe, and yet the Prophet penned it in the forme of a Pſalme: whence thus much may be noted, that it is not vnlawefull to ſing doctrine, exhortation, complaints, ſupplication, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, and ſuch like matters, as well as thankeſgiuings: briefly to ſing any portion of holy Scripture, ſo be that vnderſtanding and edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not hindred: and this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ariſeth out of this place
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13820:21"/>by analogie.</p>
               <p>The Prophet Dauid is here to be conſidered.<note place="margin">Of Dauid.</note> 1. in his owne perſon 2. ſuſtaining the perſon of a godly man. 3. as a type of Chriſt, whoſe ſufferings and glorie, whoſe prieſthood in his ſacrifice and interceſſion, with his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall office in teaching, and kingdome in gathering and guiding his Church in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, places, and times, are here not obſcurely figured: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we may note that kings and mightie men of the earth are not to ſcorne religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, as Dauid did not, the whole booke of the Pſalmes witneſseth, but with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to acquaint themſelues with holy meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of their owne eſtate, howe the matter is betwixt God and their own
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13820:22"/>ſoules: of the condition of the Church which ſhall ſuffer with Chriſt, before it be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with him, and of the doctrine of the Goſpell in the offices of Chriſt, the ſumme of the Pſalme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">to the cheif or maſter muſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>The Muſitians &amp; Singers office principally conſiſted in ſetting &amp; ſinging the Pſalmes of the Prophets, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and edification of the church: as alſo in keeping theſe holy writings ſafe for the vſe of the Church in time to come, in regard of which office the Church is called the pillar and ground of trueth: wherefore when the Prophets had compoſed any Pſalmes, they ſent them to the ſingers and muſitians, ſpecially to the principal Muſitian of any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who had the ouerſight of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13820:22"/>the reſt of his order, that they might bring them in publike for the comfort and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole church: whence this collection might be made, that if muſicke were lawfull for the Iewes, it is now for vs: and if vocall muſicke be lawefull by conſent of all, why not inſtrumentall alſo? alwaies remembring that edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication muſt not be hindered but furthered: for muſicke beeing one of the liberall arts, why is there not vſe of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke in furthering vs in the worſhip of God, as wel as of Grammar, Rhetoricke, or Logycke, &amp;c: and muſicke is not a parcell of the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lawe: and the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it in the Church, and it was vſed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13820:23"/>
               <p>Againe hence might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that it is lawful to pray the prayers compoſed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men; which was cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Church of the Iewes: who vſed to bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens pſalmes, which ſometime were prayers, into the publique aſſemblie, as for example this pſalme: and if it be ſaid that they, were vſed only dogmatically; the anſwer is, that is not ſo: <hi>for they prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God with the words of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid and Aſaph, and they bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues and worſhipped</hi> as it is euident. 2. Chron. 29.30. where beſides the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the matter, no doubt they had holy deſire &amp; wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſutable to the wordes of the prayers or thankſgiuings, as the wordes of bowing and worſhipping do plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13820:23"/>in the place alleadged: and therefore (howſoeuer ſome think) it ſeemeth to be very lawfull, to pray accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to a ſet forme: and ſo to ſay and pray the Lords prayer: ſo be that we inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate our vnderſtanding &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s into the matter of that ſet prayer which we vſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it our owne when we pray it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Concerning the morning ſtarre.</note>To thinke theſe wordes <hi>(aijeleth haſſhachar)</hi> to be the name of an inſtrument is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warrantable nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable, but coniectural: I know not what can be ſaid for it or againſt it.</p>
               <p>To think them the tune of a common ſong, or the tune of ſome ciuill ballad ſeemeth to be to accuſe the holy ghoſt for not keeping decorum,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13820:24"/>which is when holy pſalmes are ſong in the tunes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and it may be prophane ballads alſo.</p>
               <p>To tranſlate with <hi>Tremelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Iunius ad primordium aurorae,</hi> is very good, for the words may beare that reading and then they import the time of vſing the pſalme, the early morning, the time of the morning ſacrifice, ſo that this pſalme was an expoſition and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie of the ſacrifice: the ſacrifice was a type of Chriſt; this Pſalme teacheth the ſignification of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: &amp; ſo this Pſalme annexed to the ſacrifice did euery day traine vp the Church of the Iewes with a continuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and expectation of the promiſed Meſſias, whoſe ſufferings and glorie are in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13820:24"/>pſalme expresſed.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding there is another expoſition which may beſt befit the argument of the pſalme, which is this <hi>(concerning the Morning ſtar)</hi> and <hi>aijeleth</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Stellam matulina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> as well as, <hi>aſcenſum aurorae.</hi> Nowe ſeeing that this Pſalme is a prophecie of Chriſt, and that Chriſt is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly called the <hi>Bright Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtarre,</hi> Apoc. 22.16. the <hi>day ſtarre</hi> by the Apoſtle, 2. Pet. 1.19. and the <hi>day ſpring from an high,</hi> Luk 1.78. The argument of the Pſalme, and this tranſlation will very well ſort together as we ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the complaint the firſt part of the pſalme.</head>
               <p>In the complaint compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13820:25"/>in theſe two verſes may be obſerued theſed ſixe ſeuerall points to be handled,<note place="margin">My God, my God why haſt thou forſaken &amp;c.</note> which will cleare vnto vs the true meaning of the words, which are darke, and darkened more by ſome.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 How Chriſt could pray vnto God, he beeing himſelfe God equall to the father.</item>
                  <item>2 How Chriſt could pray in faith, ſeeing he could not beleeue in himſelfe?</item>
                  <item>3 How it can be ſaid that Chriſt was not heard by God when he prayed?</item>
                  <item>4 How Chriſt can be ſaid to be forſaken of God?</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe foure points apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to Chriſt, the other two concerne Dauid, &amp; the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>5 How god forſooke Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid; and how he may be ſaid
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13820:25"/>to forſake his children?</item>
                  <item>6 Laſtly the properties of faith here expreſt.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 2. O my God I cry.</note> Firſt how Chriſt God, could pray vnto God?</p>
                  <p>For the clearing of this point conſider we that Chriſt was God, and ſo paraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could not pray vnto his father, for that might ſeeme to imploy ſome diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to God the ſonne being equall to the father, &amp; open a gap for the hereſie of Arrius: but furthermore Chriſt alſo was man, and ſo made vnder the lawe, and ſo could and might, yea and ought to pray, as beeing a creature bound to worſhip the creatour: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this Chriſt beeing the mediatour of the Church ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to both his natures, he therfore prayed according
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13820:26"/>to both his natures:<note place="margin">My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> thus: his manhood actiuely powring forth prayer, his godhead dignifying his prayer, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it meritorious and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing audience.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt prayed to his father therefore, as man, and as the mediatour.</p>
                  <p>Now if it be alledged that ſeing himſelfe was God hee muſt therfore pray vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which may ſeeme ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, or els if he do exclude himſelfe, then committ idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: the anſwer is that he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his father directly and primarily, in reſpect of order the father being the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Trinitie ordine; but indirectly, incluſiuelie, and ſecondarily he praied to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the holy Ghoſt alſo: here the diſtinction of nature
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13820:26"/>and perſon muſt be admitted neceſſarily: againe it may be ſuppoſed that no abſurditie would followe, if we ſay that the ſecond perſon in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie did pray vnto the firſt, that is, did teſtifie his will to haue the Church ſaued: but that is abuſiuely in very hard Catachreſis.</p>
                  <p>In ſumme: it is no abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſay that a man may pray to himſelfe, that is, perſwade himſelfe to grant that which is for his owne aduantage: for as affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or deſire ſometime obtaineth of a man that which his iudgement diſalloweth: (which is a kinde of praier or intreatie:) or contrariwiſe, as the iudgement perſwadeth the affection that which it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliketh: ſo Chriſt-man may aske ſomething of Chriſt-God:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13820:27"/>and no abſurdity (as it ſeemeth) be admitted,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Secondly: how Chriſt could pray in faith?<note place="margin">V. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, My God</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the further enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this doubt a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. Faith is legall and euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall; of the law, and of the goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Faith required in the lawe Adam had in paradiſe and Chriſt had when he prayed whereby the creature relieth it ſelfe vpon the creatour for all manner of good things &amp; deliuerance from all euill, if Chriſt had wanted this faith he had not preſently obeyed the law, which to ſay were to blaſpheme.</p>
                  <p>Euangelicall faith or the faith required in the goſpell is that whereby the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13820:27"/>relieth it ſelfe vpon God, through Chriſt and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour: beleeuing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all good things from him, by the meanes of Chriſt: now although Chriſt were made vnder the lawe, yet he was not made vnder the goſpell, for he was not bound to faith and repentance as ſinners are, himſelfe beeing without ſinne: he is the matter and author of the Goſpell: wherefore to the Chriſt to the obedience of the law through and by vertue of the Goſpell as we are tied, is to ſuppoſe him ſinfull by making him his owne ſauiour.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore to anſwer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly: Chriſt praied a legall prayer as Adam did but Chriſt praied not an euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall prayer: (except
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13820:28"/>we vnderſtand an euangeli-praier in this ſenſe, that he made interceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs, which may rather be called a meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious praier:) Chriſt praied in faith of gods infinite mercy, but not in faith of the pardon of ſinne through a Sauiour, which he needed not: and which we neede.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Thirdly: Howe was Chriſt not heard when he praied?<note place="margin">V. 2 But thou heareſt not. V. 1. Farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the words of my roaring,</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no contradictions in holy ſcriptures: although there may ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time ſeeme ſhew of oppoſition: we read in the Heb. 5.7. that <hi>Chriſt was hard from that which be feared:</hi> here in this place we read that god did not heare Chriſt, but was farre from the wordes of his roaring: in ſhew here is an oppoſition, but in ſubſtance,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13820:28"/>things being aright diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, there is none.</p>
                  <p>The art of reaſon teacheth that one rule of oppoſition is, that the thinges oppoſed be oppoſite in the ſame ſence: (<hi>ſecundum idem</hi> as the logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay) now Chriſt was hard in one ſence, and he was not heard in another ſence: and ſo the prophet &amp; the Apoſtle are not oppoſite: wherefore thus theſe two places are both verified, and may well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
                  <p n="1">Chriſt was heard in that he was not ſwallowed vp of the wrath of god, but was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from it, and from the power of our ſpirituall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: &amp; again. Chriſt was not heard in that gods wrath ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon him, and poſſeſſed his ſoule a competent ſeaſon:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13820:29"/>or thus:</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt was heard in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the conditions of his praier, (if it be poſſible, and if it be thy will:) and againe:</p>
                  <p>Chriſt was not heard in regard of the petition abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conſidered, without conditions: or thus.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Chriſt was heard, as the children of God are heard, to whome ſometime the Lord denieth the very particular thing they aske, and in liewe thereof giueth them a thing as good or better then it: 2. Cor. 12.8, 9. So the Lord did not deliuer Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wrath: for <hi>he taſted the cuppe of his wrath,</hi> as he ſaith, Math. 20.22. But the Lord gaue him power and ſtrength, and grace to beare it, and to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13820:29"/>vanquiſh it at the length: for euen then did hee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the wrath of God when Gods wrath killed him.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things beeing thus diſtinguiſhed, we ſee the Prophet in this pſalme, and the Apoſtle in the Hebrews are not at variance, &amp; ſo we perceiue alſo howe Chriſt was not heard when he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me: art art ſo far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e from my health?</note>Fourthly: howe Chriſt was forſaken of God? That this point may the better be conceiued, let it be conſidered: Negatiuely, howe he was not forſaken: &amp; affirmatiuely howe he was forſaken.</p>
                  <p>Negatiuely thus: Chriſt was not forſaken any of theſe foure waies following.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13820:30"/>
                  <p>Firſt the eſſence of the godhead was neuer ſeuered or excluded from Chriſt the man, but it dwelt in him at all times fully: Coloſſ. 2.9.</p>
                  <p>Secondly the perſonall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the two natures was neuer diſſolued: and ſo the perſon of the ſonne neuer forſooke the humanitie of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the power of the godhead alſo was alwaies preſent with him, enabling him to beare the full viall of Gods wrath.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the gratious aſsiſtance of Gods ſpirit was neuer wanting, inabling Chriſt without the leaſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencie, diſtruſt, &amp;c. to beare whatſoeuer was infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vpon him for our ſins.</p>
                  <p>Thus Negatiuely Chriſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13820:30"/>was not forſaken of the nature, perſon, power, and grace of God. Howe then was he forſaken?</p>
                  <p>Affirmatiuely therefore he was forſaken: both poſitiuely in that God the father pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon him the infinite ſea of his wrath, which hee nowe felt: and priuatiuely in that he was bereft and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of all comfortable: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; the godhead for a ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhaddowing it ſelfe vnder the cloude of Gods wrath, that the manhood of Chriſt might feele the intollerable burden thereof: and thus Chriſt bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of conſolation complaineth that he was forſaken. But Chriſt beeing thus forſaken, he ſuſtayned the wrath of God, ſtriued with it, and ſubdued it; that is,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13820:31"/>he deliuered both himſelfe and vs from it, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly finiſhed the worke of our redemption.</p>
                  <p>But if any man thinke it a thing vnreaſonable, or rather a blaſphemie, that it ſhould bee auouched that Chriſt ſuffered Gods wrath which is commonly called the paines of hell, he muſt remember a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ought to bee made betwixt the paines of hell, and the damnation of hell: Chriſt ſuffered not the damnation of hell but the paines of hell.</p>
                  <p>The paines of hell are only the ſenſe of exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the want of all comfort and conſolation: commonly called, <hi>paena</hi> and <hi>damnum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13820:31"/>
                  <p>The damnation of hell are certaine neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents which followe the foreſaid paines of hell in the meere creature: as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the ſoule of Iudas nowe in hell: beſides that it is depriued of all comfort, which is a loſſe: and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which is the paine: deſpaireth, wanteth faith, hope, loue, the feare of god, patience, and is affrighted with an accuſing and gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſcience, and beſides all this, is bound in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting chaines to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day in a certaine place which is called Hell.</p>
                  <p>Nowe for the application of the diſtinction: Chriſt if hee had beene a meere
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13820:32"/>man, could not haue eſcaped part of the damnation of hel, when gods wrath was ſo fully powred out vpon him: but it ſhould haue fallen out to him as it falleth out with the deuill and reprobates: but becauſe Chriſt was God alſo, his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head did infinitely ſtrengthen and grace his manhood, ſo as none of all theſe accidents which neceſsarily growe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a meere creature, ſeazed vpon him, as deſpaire, impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;c. therefore to ſay that Chriſt ſuffered the wrath of God which may be called the paines of hell, is neither blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous nor vnreaſonable, this diſtinction of hell paines and damnation beeing admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>Thus the foure points ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to Chriſt are clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13820:32"/>now the other two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Dauid follow:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Fiftly: Howe God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh Dauid and his children?<note place="margin">Forſaken me.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>God forſaketh his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two waies principally.</p>
                  <p>Firſt by giuing them to their own hearts luſts in part, and permitting them to the temptations of the deuill: and ſuffering them to fall into ſome ſinnes which wracke &amp; torment the conſcience: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which Dauid praieth, Pſal. 119.8. And Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to pray in the laſt petition of the Lords praier: <hi>Lead vs not into temptation, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly by cauſing them to ſee and feele the wrath of God in ſome meaſure and for ſome time, till humiliation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13820:33"/>be wrought in them through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſome ſinnes. So Dauid was humbled Pſal. 6. and 15. and ſo are all the children of God in ſome meaſure: and thus the Lord forſooke Dauid, both by permitting him to fall into ſinne, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to feele the ſmart of Gods wrath as a meanes of humiliation for that ſinne: and thus the Lord forſaketh his children oft times, as they haue experience of: which may teach vs charitie in cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring men whome wee ſee ſtraungly caſt downe with fearefull humiliation, they may be neuertheleſſe deere children of God, although it may bee alſo that they haue fallen into ſome gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes as Dauid did: and yet happily alſo this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13820:33"/>humiliation may growe vpon infirmities with ſome tender heart: and for ſuch vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble critickes that thus intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately cenſure humbled conſciences, they are to know that ſome kind of deſpaire is better then hardnes of heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Sixtly, what are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of faith here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?<note place="margin">My God, forſaken me.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two properties of faith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently appeare in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, when God forſaketh, then to hold faſt, when God killeth then to truſt in him as Iob. 13.15. who profeſſeth that <hi>though the L. ſhould ſtay him yet he would truſt,</hi> and Dauid els where ſaith, <hi>that though he was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time affraid yet he truſted in god</hi> for faith holdeth faſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13820:34"/>when all reaſon faileth as Abraham (Rom 4.18.19.) beleeued a thing in nature &amp; reaſon impoſſible that a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of nintie yeares, ſhould conceiue with child of a man that was an hundred yeare old: ſo doth Dauid in this place: God forſaketh him, &amp; yet he calleth him his god.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond propertie of faith is particular application, whereby Chriſt with all his merittes are appropriated by the beleeuer to his owne ſoule in ſpeciall and he is truly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the pardon of his ſin &amp; the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſoule Ro. 8.38. Ioh. 20.28. ſome think it preſumption for any man ſo to ſay: and none haue euer attained to this certen aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but thoſe to whome god hath reuealed it: but wee are to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13820:34"/>know that there muſt be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference made between faith, and coniecture: Faith is kow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which hath a certaintie in it whoſe <hi>genus</hi> is <hi>ſcientia:</hi> Coniecture is knowledge which hath vncertaintie in it, whoſe <hi>genus</hi> is <hi>opinio:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that denie the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of faith and ſaluation, make faith coniecturall and confound faith and opinion which is abſurd.</p>
                  <p>Now indeed faith is neuer without doubting, and yet faith is certain ſtil: for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion and knowledge is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a true perſwaſion, or a full perſwaſion: a true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or a full knowledge: as there is difference betwixt a true man, &amp; a perfect full &amp; complete man: a man wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a hand is a man indeed:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13820:35"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: euen ſo of faith, and aſſurance: True perſwaſion is <hi>fides</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> where in there is no hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Full perſwaſion is <hi>fidei</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which hath no doubting, which no man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving hath or can haue till loue be perfected, when alſo faith ſhall be caſt out, yet we are to ſtriue againſt doubting, and ſtill to pray: <hi>Lord encreaſe our faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which ſome might comment vpon the expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Why forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, &amp;c.</note> whereas he asketh a reaſon why God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoke him alſo? the two ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctes of his prayer, that he prayed with roaring and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and day and night and had no eaſe, I omit as ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie matters: only thus much.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt expoſtulateth and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13820:35"/>debateth the matter of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion with God, not for that he knewe not wherefore he was forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but complaining moſt pittiouſly of his extream miſerie: neither is here any ſuſpition of impatiencie at all: no God forbid:</p>
                  <p>Againe Chriſts roaring &amp; crying, that is, his feruent praier, alſo his continuance in praier day and night, are for our example in the like caſes, that in our extremities we neuer ceaſe crying till God giue eaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>The groundes of the Prophets faith.<note place="margin">V. 3. Thou art holy, &amp; doeſt inhabite the praiſes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>God is holy <hi>Effectiuè</hi> and <hi>ſubiectiuè:</hi> for he is both the worker of holineſſe and the fountaine of holineſſe: nowe both theſe are here ſignified by the Prophet: namely, that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13820:36"/>God is the author and worker of holineſſe in the Church. And the Emphaſis of the ſpeech is to be obſerued, in the pronoune <hi>attah (thou)</hi> which is excluſiue, as if the Prophet had ſaid <hi>(thou onely:)</hi> which is the golden ſentence written in the high Prieſts Miter, Exod. 28.20. <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſanctification of the Church is the worke of God only:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Doctrine.</note> which doctrine for that it is a very materiall point, is firſt to be expounded, and then confirmed. It may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded or amplified by the particular cauſes of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein the Lord hath the maine ſtroke, or els the worke ſucceedeth not; as by induction appeareth thus.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 God is the originall and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13820:36"/>fundamentall cauſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, purgation and ſanctification of the Church, who of his owne loue and compaſſion to mans miſery prouided redemption for vs, there being nothing out of himſelfe to mooue him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Chriſts ſacrifice is the meritorious and purchaſing cauſe, for he paid the price of redemption for vs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Chriſts kingdome that is his reſurrection, aſcenſion, ſeſſion at the right (hand) of his father is the effectuall, operatiue, and working cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The word in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of teaching, praying, celebrating the ſacramentes and diſcipline eccleſiaſtical is the inſtrumentall cauſe, where if any man thinke that the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13820:37"/>meanes are any thing without God giue the increaſe he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth the Apoſtles ſpeech 1. Cor. 3.7. for the word which is the power of God to ſaluation is not the bare ſound or letter, but it is the inward ſpirit of powar and grace annexed thereto: which is Chriſts Scepter.</p>
                  <p>So that ſeeing the loue of God, the ſacrifice, kingdome and ſcripture of Chriſt are the only cauſes of our ancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, it is plaine that the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctification and clenſing of the church is gods worke only.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine thus cleared may alſo be prooued and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by induction of thoſe things which are in or with ſinne, the which none but God can take away and they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13820:37"/>are theſe foure.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Tranſgreſſion which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth Gods lawe &amp; iuſtice which in ſinne is violated for <hi>ſinne is the tranſgreſſion of the lawe</hi> &amp;c. 1. Ioh. 3.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Corruption reſpecting the ſinner; which followeth the tranſgreſſion as the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary effect thereof: as in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Guilt whereby the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tranſgreſſing and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted is culpable of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Puniſhment the iuſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and deſert of ſinne, which is Gods wrath and the curſe of the law Gal. 3.10</p>
                  <p>Now no creature can take away any of theſe, it is the worke of god alone therefore was it that our redeemer was God.</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:13820:38"/>
                  <p>Remiſſion of ſinne, which is the taking away of the guilt and puniſhment of ſinne is that worke of God onely. Micah 7.18. Exod 34.7. Mar. 2.7. Eſay. 43.25.1. Ioh. 3.8.</p>
                  <p>Againe ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is the purgation and ſtaine of ſinne which is imprinted in our ſoules (whether it be a qualitie poſitiue, or priuatiue) is the only worke of god. Iob. 13.4.1. Theſ. 5.23.</p>
                  <p>Seeing then the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, guilt, and puniſhment of ſinne which are three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall matters appertaining to ſinne are only taken away by god, becauſe they conteyning the violation of an infinite iuſtice, are after a ſort, infinite and ſo cannot be taken away but by ſome perſon infinite,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13820:38"/>Gods infinite iuſtice beeing able to ouerwhelme a meere creature euery way finit, it followeth therefore by ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable conſequence that ſin alſo is taken away by God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for the corruption, guilt, and puniſhment of ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboliſhed, the auomie or tranſgreſion is remoued and reckoned as not done, which is alſo a fruit of remiſſion of ſinne, and of this the Lord ſaith that he wil caſt it into the bottome of the ſea, he will forget and remember it no more, Micah. 7.19. Ierem, 31.33. Ezech. 18.22.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine thereof is thus confirmed and cleered: and it hath an excellent vſe to vs not onely for coniectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the papiſts, which auouch temporall puniſhment ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13820:39"/>by the creature to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſatisfaction for ſome ſinnes and that good workes ſhall deſerue grace, and that the prieſt can iudicially par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſinne, all which are ſo many blaſphemies againſt the mercy of God, the ſacrifice kingdome and ſcepter of Chriſt, but eſpecially it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for our inſtruction to teach vs to quake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the fearefull condition of ſinne, which can no other way be aboliſhed but by the omnipotent power of God encountring (as it were) the infinite wrath of God, and vanquiſhing it, to teach vs to take heed of committing the leaſt ſinne, which none but God can aboliſh: which alſo called the Lord Ieſus Chriſt from heauen; for this cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:13820:39"/>appeared the ſonne of God that he might diſſolue the workes of the deuill: for the papiſts deeme too lightlie of ſinne that thinke ſome ſinnes veniall in their own nature, &amp; the profane multitude offer violence to Gods iuſtice in threatning kindneſſe vpon his mercy, ſaying of ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences as Lott ſaid of Zoar <hi>oh it is but a little one; and God is mercifull:</hi> is it ſuppoſe we a ſmall ſinne that, for redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming whereof, God muſt needs become man and die?</p>
                  <p>God is the owner and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of his Church, and ſo conſequently of the praiſe &amp; worſhippe which is in the church offred him continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for God decreeing from all eternitie the glorie of his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13820:40"/>mercy and iuſtice, and the reſt of his moſt excellent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes (which are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called his Name in the ſcripture decreed alſo to haue a Church; and a ſauiour for his Church: without whome neither could he haue a church, nor be glorified out of himſelfe if hee wanted a Church: Wherefore Chriſt praieth thus: if thou wilt be glorified and praiſed out of thy ſelfe, thou muſt haue a Church: if thou wilt haue a Church, thou muſt haue a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: if thou wilt haue a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, then ſaue me who am-appointed the Sauiour: and ſo the <hi>ſorites</hi> is concluded: if thou wilt be praiſed, ſaue me.</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt be praiſed &amp;c. <hi>ergo</hi> ſaue me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doctrine.</note>Gods gloly and praiſe is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13820:40"/>the ende of the worlde, the Church, and of Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For to this ende hath God created the world, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed his Church, and appointed Chriſt the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Church, that he might be glorified: as the wiſe man ſaith: <hi>God made all things for his glorie:</hi> Prou. 16.4. So ſaith the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 3.22.23. <hi>All things are yours, you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods:</hi> that is to ſay, Chriſt hath redeemed all things for your vſe, that you may worſhip Chriſt, and God through Chriſt may be glorified.</p>
                  <p>The vſe of this doctrine is to teach vs to glorifie God which is attained by a godly life, and two reaſons may be alleadged for this purpoſe.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13820:41"/>
                  <p n="1">1 Neceſſity: for if we doe not glorifie God mercy by godlineſſe and honeſtie in this life, he will be glorified by vs in his iuſtice in our vtter deſtruction after this life: for euery man ſhallbe either an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of glorifying god in his mercy, or ſeruing for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the glory of his iuſtice.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Analogie and proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for we ſee all the creatures by naturall inſtinct without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and rebellion are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed readily and ſpeedily to there end, there place, and vſe; as the ſunne &amp;c. Pſal. 19.4.5. and Pſalme 104. <hi>toto:</hi> ſo that if we degenerate from this end which God hath apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs we are the onely irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular perſons of the world, and indeed men and angels are ſo: wherefore if gods loue,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13820:41"/>Chriſts death, euerlaſting life will not, yet lett feare &amp; ſhame mooue vs to obedience.</p>
                  <p>To conclud this verſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing god ſanctifieth his church and children, and will ſurely ſanctifie them that he may be praiſed by them, hence doth ariſe matter of conſolation &amp; thankfullnes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Of conſolation thus; if we be caſt downe with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of ſinne committed and raigning in vs, ſo as that, though we pray and heare, &amp; read, and partake in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and diſcipline our own ſoules, and watch our hart &amp; ſences with all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet we cannot obtaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt ouer our ſins, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto the Lord, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his holines; that though
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13820:42"/>we cannot ouermaſter our own corruption, yet the Lord can and will in due time, for holines appertaineth to the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of thankfulnes thus: therefore doth the Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from the bondage of our ſpirituall enemies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth he redeeme, purge, and ſanctifie his Church that he might be glorified by his Church; ſo doth the prophet reaſon pſal. 103. v. 1.2.3.4. &amp; ſo doth Zachary. Luk. 1.74.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">V. 4. Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers truſted in thee, they called vpon thee, and were deliuered and not confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>God is immutable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable in his loue and he remaineth as firme in his faith to the Church as euer he was: for he keepeth his fidelitie for euer and with him there is no variablenes, nor ſhadowe of change; and ſeeing therefore the fathers in the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13820:42"/>were deliuered through the mercy and truth of God through the promiſed meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, now alſo the poſteritie, &amp; namly Chriſt himſelfe the promiſed ſeed muſt needs alſo be deliuered from periſhing.</p>
                  <p>From this place then we learne diuers inſtructions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt that Chriſt was the <hi>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b ſlain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world.</hi> Apoc. 13.8. and he <hi>by his blood purged the ſinnes of the former teſtament:</hi> Heb 9.15. and therfore howſoeuer the Papiſts teach and deliuer that there was <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> a certain skirt of hell, where the fathers were reſerued vntill Chriſt had ouercome death, &amp; opened heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet we may confidently beleeue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly auouch by this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that there was no
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13820:43"/>ſuch thing, for ſeeing the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers truſted in God and called vpon him, they were therefore deliuered, and not confounded, as the text ſaith: but if they were in <hi>Limbo,</hi> they were confounded and not deliuered: for there as the Papiſts dreame is <hi>paena dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> though not <hi>paena ſenſus,</hi> it is a dungeon of darknes, and a pit that wil hold no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as they will needs haue it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">V. 4. Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers truſted in thee and were deliuered.</note>Secondly: that by analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie and proportion the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of Chriſts death alſo, muſt be ſtretcht to the worlds end, as wel as to the world of beginning. For as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.</note> out of the Prophet, Chriſt is a prieſt for euer, after the order of Melchizedech, as well as he was a lamb ſlaine from the beginning of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13820:43"/>world: &amp; as his blood ſerued for the purgation of the ſins of the former teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which liued before Chriſt was ſlain, ſo alſo it ſerueth for the clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Church which nowe ſtandeth vp after his death: for it is meere blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to include the vertue of Chriſts ſacrifice within the compaſſe of a fewe houres wherin he ſuffered his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whence another popiſh opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath the neck broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, which is, that there needeth a daiely ſacrificing of Chriſt in the maſſe after an vnbloodie manner, which is as doltiſh a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as that other of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice applicatorie and not propitiatorie: for ſo farre forth as the Euchariſt appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it is a Sacrament and not a ſacrifice: and ſo farre
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13820:44"/>forth as the ſacrifice is vnbloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die it is Euchariſticall, and not propitiatory: for without blood there is no propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly. Faithfull praier is neuer diſappointed but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies obtaineth,<note place="margin">V 5. They cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon thee and were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</note> as Chriſt ſaith, Mat. 7.7. <hi>Aske and yee ſhall receiue,</hi> but we muſt aske in faith: for otherwiſe though we aske we ſhall not receiue, becauſe we aske a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, as Iames ſaith. Therfore faith is the neceſſarie conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of obtaining: and ſo of true praier: but faith is grounded vpon Gods word which is his will: and Gods word and will is, that we aske nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his glory, the good of the church, or our own ſoules health; for when we aske any thing derogating from gods
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13820:44"/>glorie, our prayers are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blaſphemies: and when we deſire any thing hindring the ſaluation of our owne ſoules, or the Churches good, we curſe our ſelues &amp; the church: Wherefore we muſt alwaies remember to examine our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions by gods word, that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them agreeable thereto, we may be bold to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God; finding them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, we may learne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie our ſelues, our wits and wils, and all we haue, and ſo caſt down our ſelues at Gods feete, &amp; ſay as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Thy will be done and not mine:</hi> thus if we doe in praier, we ſhall obtaine what we aske, as Chriſt alſo did when he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that praier: Hebr. 5.7.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">V. 4. Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</note> it is profitable for vs to obſerue the dealing of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13820:45"/>God with his children in time paſt: and from thence to gather hope to our ſelues: for ſeeing God is as able, mercifull, and true, as euer he was, therefore we may aſſure our ſelues of helpe from god in time of neede beeing Gods ſeruants, as well as our forefathers: remembring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the Apoſtles rule. Rom. 15.4. that we may haue hope; But that we may obtaine hope, we muſt haue the conſolation of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods goodneſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in the ſcriptures to his children, and eſpecially to Chriſt the head of the church, as that place importeth, and further alſo we muſt haue <hi>patience, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue done the will of God we may obtaine the promiſe.</hi> Heb. 10.36.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:13820:45"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>v. 6.7.8.</bibl> 
                     <p>
                        <hi>But I am a woman and not a man: a ſhame of men and the contempt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>All that ſee me haue me in deriſion: they make a mowe, and nod the head: ſaying.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee truſted in the Lord, let him deliuer him: let him ſaue him ſeeing he loueth him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The prophet Dauid was either annointed or crowned king without queſtion when this pſalme was penned, and yet we ſe he was thus ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed by wicked men; Chriſt himſelfe the moſt holy and righteous man and the moſt excellent and worthie perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euer the earth cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet we ſe is expoſed to the contumelious mocks of wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; For this is the portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:13820:46"/>of Gods children (as it was one part of Chriſts ſufferings) to be diſhonoured, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and derided: the hiſtorie of the Goſpell is plentifull in this point, they diſhonor him in charging him with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, with breach of the Sabbath, with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritaniſme, which is to caſt out deuils by the deuill, &amp;c. when he was condemned to die they mocke him, attiring him deſpitefully as a king, with a crowne of thornes, with a garment of purple, with a ſcepter of a reede: as if he had beene a king a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt fooles, boyes, or Pigmies: they buffet him, they ſpit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, they ſmite him, whip him, and in ſumme, they mocke at his kingdome and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13820:46"/>propheticall office: this befell Chriſt the head of the church, the maſter of the houſe: and ſhall his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers or hou-ſhold ſeruants thinke to eſcape? it is enough for the ſeruant to be as his maſter is: and the foote muſt not thinke to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the piercing with nailes, when the head was crowned and wounded with thornes.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon why Chriſt was thus content to be abaſed was, that he might deliuer vs from eternall ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, which is the due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of ſinne: and to ſanctifie the euill name and ſlaunder, which we ſuſtaine now for his ſake, and for our owne good, that though an euill name be euill, and a curſe, yet the Lord hath by his reproach taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the malignitie of reproch
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13820:47"/>and ſlaunder from vs: yet he hath left ſhame for vs ſtill to ſuſtaine, that we might fulfill the remnant of the afflictions: he hath drunke the full cup, and we muſt pledge him in the bottome of the cuppe: we muſt therefore learne to deny our ſelues, and namely (as this argument implieth) our good name and fame: not that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not by al good meanes preſerue his good name, but that a man be not too popular without meaſure and by vnlawfull meanes to ſeeke a good name, many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beeing too greedie (as Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops dogge) catch at the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and looſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, while they ſeeke fame and report, they leeſe a good name: for he that immoderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnlawefully ſeeketh
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13820:47"/>to get and keepe his credit with all ſorts of perſons, ſhall get a fame from the wicked, which is but the ſhaddowe, and leeſe a good name from the godly, which is the ſubſtance. A good name is the reward of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and the feare of God: Prou. 22.4. <hi>and God will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them that honour him:</hi> 1. Sam. 2.3. And by faith we ſhall obtaine a good report as the Elders did, Hebr. 11.2. By ſuch meanes we may ſeeke to get a good name, which will be a good oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the children of god refreſhing them with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of a godly life, Eccleſ. 7.1. But if any of Gods children are too curious of their credit, and too much addicted to be popular,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13820:48"/>the Lord will really teach the to denie themſelues in this point, and by cauſing wicked men to ſlaunder them, will teach them by a reall ſermon that which by the word and inſtruction they cannot learn: which is to forſake their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit for Chriſts ſake, as Chriſt did forſake his owne excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, and deiected himſelfe to the greateſt indignities that a man could ſuffer, for our ſakes: in ſo much as the ſcripture ſaith, he did annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late himſelfe, that is, he was content to be in no account; that we might be pretiouſly eſteemed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and nod the head.</note>The wrying of the mouth, and nodding the head are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuill, fooliſh, and deſpitefull geſtates, ſuch as ciuil, diſcreet, and moderate men would
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13820:48"/>haue beene aſhamed to vſe: but if malice haue got the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the necke, howe will not wicked men tranſgreſſe the lawe of ciuill and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous behauiour? yea the fence of nature and humanitie they will trample flat to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as if they loſt both ciuilitie and manhood: which point may further appeare in the mocking ſpeeches which they vtter againſt Chriſt now hanging vpon the croſſe:<note place="margin">Let him deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, &amp;c.</note> which mocking geſtures and ſpeeches ſhewe more then barbarous deſpight, and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh malice: for a perſon that is condemned to die, yea nowe in execution is pittied and praied for by all the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yea euen the hearts of Adamant then will ſoften to here a man in extremitie of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13820:49"/>paine readie to die, yet then theſe monſters of men and nature are neuer a whit aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged towards him, but reioyce then at his woe, and ſcoffe at his fall: ſaying: God hath forſaken him, he loueth him not, he neuer did truſt in god, as he pretended: for then ſurely God would not ſuffer him to periſh, but would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him: or if he himſelfe were a ſauiour he would ſaue himſelfe and others and come downe from the croſſe, that we might know him to be the ſauiour and beleeue in him: but we are to know theſe things are otherwiſe, for God may loue a man, and a man may truſt in God, and yet ſtill continue in affliction: ſo we ſe the martyrs die for Chriſt and periſs;h in regard of the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13820:49"/>outward man, &amp; that the loue God, and God loueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtil: and ſo was it with Chriſt a which may ſerue to muſſel the mouths of the wicked world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that preſently think gods children, forſaken of god, and that they are naughty perſons becauſe they ſuſtain the croſſe &amp; ſometime fall vnder it: nay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe they ſhould thinke it a ſigne of Gods hatred not to be vnder the croſſe as it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with many wicked men, that thus the Lord fatteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the day of ſlaughter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ 9 &amp; 10</note>
                  <hi>But thou didſt draw me out: of the womb: thou gaueſt me hope as my mothers breaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I was caſt vpon thee eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the womb: thou art my god from my mothers belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howſoeuer theſe murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Chirſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:13820:50"/>with him that he aſſureth himſelfe of Gods fauour and mercifull protection ſtill, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he had ſo graciouſly preſerued him, euen from the birth, the womb, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: For God did by an eſpecial prouidence watch ouer Chriſt in all ages and times of his life, yea euen at his conception, when he was to be framed in his mothers womb: which thing may a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle be conſidered of in this manner following.</p>
               <p>The Lord preſerued Chriſt in his conception from the contagion of ſinne, he beeing framed of the ſubſtance of the virgin by the power or the holy ghoſt without the helpe of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, by reaſon whereof the courſe of originall ſinne was ſtayed which is deriued to vs
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13820:50"/>in generation: wherefore in this ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Chriſt had no father.</p>
               <p>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his birth alſo hee was preſerued by the ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, that he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed not, though hee was borne in the ſtable and laid in the cratch, and wanted the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinary helpes which women in ſuch caſes haue for their childe at there natiuite: for it is probable they wanted a fire, the ſtable beeing no fit place for that purpoſe, beſides the vnhealthſome ſauor of the ſtable &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his education and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, he was kept from the conſpiracy of Herod that ſought his life, when his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fled into Egipt to ſaue his life: alſo when the innocents were ſlayne: when he was loſt by his parents and found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13820:51"/>diſputing with the doctors in the temple. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his life when he was called forth to the execution of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorſhip after his baptiſme, he was preſerud from many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiraces of the high prieſt and the phariſes, and the rulers of the people, who ſought to haue ſlayne him, but he was preſerued by the Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce till the appointed time.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing god had watched ouer him all his daies hitherto hee nowe fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth himſelfe of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and aſſiſtance at this brunt alſo.</p>
               <p>And as this is true in Chriſt the head ſo alſo after a certaine manner is it true in his members, all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, ouer whome the Lord watcheth by his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13820:51"/>gracious preſeruation, and that in there conception Iob. 10.10.11. and Pſal. 139.13.14.15.16. which two places beeing viewed doe largely expreſſe this point: as alſo in there whole life: Pſal. 121. <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> Which may ſerue to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the poore members of Chriſt, that peraduenture might think by reaſon of there baſe reſpect themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be regarded by God, ſeeing the world ſo litle regard them; ſurely they are to knowe that he hath nombred there bones, and all there me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are written in his booke, yea he knoweth the nomber of the heares of their head: &amp; therefore in this regard they may be comforted: Lazarus was poore and yet the Lords angels miniſtred to him. lu. 16</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:13820:52"/>
               <p>Laſtly from the force of the argument, vſed here to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the faith of the prophet in aſſurance of future mercy grounded vpon former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience thereof we are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icle &amp; record vp, and as it were hang vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the file, all the fauour of Gods mercy vouchſafed vs, that from thence in time of need, we may gather faith &amp; comfort: for our faith is weak, and a litle thing will not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs in extremitie, we had need therefore to write a booke of remembrance of all the former experience of Gods mercy thereby to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our infirmity: ſo Dauid did when he was animated to encounter with Goliah.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:13820:52"/>
               <head>The requeſt or petiton of the Prophet propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. 11.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <p>
                        <hi>Be not farre from me, becauſe trouble is neere, and there is none to helpe. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Out of this verſe two things may be gathered: firſt that a Godly man may be troubled and helples: as was Chriſt, &amp; the prophet in this place. All Chriſts apoſtles forſoke him, euen Peter that profeſſed the contrary, and at the firſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more forward then the reſt by fighting for him: yea &amp; Iohn whome Chriſt loued came away without his coate where Chriſt was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: The Apoſtle Paul. 2. Tim. 4.16 ſaith that <hi>when he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13820:53"/>was to appeare before Caeſar all men forſooke him:</hi> for indeede there be very few or none to be found that dare and will ſtand out boldlie to helpe in time of neede, that dare che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a man that is perſecuted for the truth: although they wiſh the cauſe and the perſon well, yet they dare not be ſeen throughly in the matter, but then Chriſt ſhal ſhift for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if his life be once called in queſtion: now therefore if we ſe gods children thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and helpeles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them not, conclude not there vpon that they are naught, for the deare children of God, yea Chriſt himſelfe was afflicted and deſolate that that is helpleſſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly heare note we, that though the world offoard
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13820:53"/>no helpe to Gods childrens though all forſake them, yet the Lord will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them: ſo ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2. Timoth. 4.17. So ſaith Chriſt, Ioh. 16.32. though Chriſt were alone and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate in regarde of mans helpe and comfort, yet he was not alone, but the father was with him, and though Paul was helpeleſse when he appeared before Nero the Emperour, yet God deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him out of the Lyons mouth; for God wil either deliuer, or giue ſtrength and patience to beare the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: which is matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: this the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren knew right wel, Dan. 3.17, 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which were threatned with the fierie furnace, which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13820:54"/>miniſtred comfort to them in deadly danger: with this the Prophet encouraged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Pſal. 23. <hi>To walke fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly through the valley of the ſhaddowe of death,</hi> conſidering Gods preſence with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The affliction that immediately ſeazed vpon Chriſts ſoule.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Verſ. 12, 13, 14, 15.</note>
                        <hi>12. Many Bulls haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me, mightie buls of Baſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue cloſed me about.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>13. They gape vpon me with their mouthes, as a ramping and roaring lyon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>14. I am like water powred out, and all my bones are diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: mine heart is like waxe, it is molten in the middes of my bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>15. My ſtrength is dried
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13820:54"/>vp like a potſheard, and my tongue cleaueth to my lawes, &amp; thou haſt brought me into the duſt of death.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The Apoſtle Peter: 1. Pet. 5.8. calleth the deuill a <hi>roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lyon, who goeth about con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſeeking whome he may deuour:</hi> and in this place the Prophet ſaith, that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies gaped vpon him like a ramping and roaring lyon: whence probably may bee coniectured (the two proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a lyon fitting ſo wel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither both here in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and alſo in the Apoſtle) that the enemies that now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Chriſt were, the deuill and his angels.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Pet. 5.8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 22.13. <hi>arich—ſhoag—toreph.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:13820:55"/>
               <p>Wherefore we will take it as graunted, that in this place the Prophet foretelleth the ſufferings that directly and properly and primarily befell Chriſts ſoule: which may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be prooued by the ſtrange effects which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet rehearſeth, verſ. 14.15. that followed his affliction: as the diſſolution of al the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule, or the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting their functions, which the compaſſing and incloſure and gaping of his enemies, could not worke in him: &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine whereas in the v. 21. he deſireth to be deliuered from the lyons mouth, how can this be expounded but of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Gods wrath, nowe vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; enforced by the deuill againſt him: in regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he deſireth to be deliuered:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13820:55"/>all theſe things compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither carie me eaſily to think that here the affliction proper to Chriſts ſoule is expreſſed. Therefore the might, malice, and miſcheife of the deuils are here to be conſidered, who in this place are called mightie Bulls, and a raping &amp; roaring lyon, there being one deuil the cheife, and the reſt conſenting and conſpiring with him.</p>
               <p>The power of the deuils appeares in this, that they are angels, and although through their fall they haue loſt grace and glory, yet their other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which the Lord endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with in their creation remaine: as namely their ſtrength: now the ſtrength of an angell is wonderfull great (though not infinite:) as may appeare, in that the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13820:56"/>angel ouerthrewe in the hoaſt of the Aſſyrians in one night, an hundreth foure ſcore and fiue thouſand, Eſay, 37.36. Alſo in the time of Dauid ſeauentie thouſand in three daies, 2. Sam. 24.15. And in Egypt euill angels deſtroyed all the firſt borne of Egypt. Pſal. 78.49.50.51. And as it may ſeeme in a peece of a night: yea ſurely it is likely, that if God ſhould permit, the deuils were able to deſtroy all the men, and all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world, and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle heauen and earth togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>The malice of the deuill is as great if not greater then his power, which may appeare in two particulars: firſt in that he ſetteth himſelfe againſt God and Chriſt, whereas he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13820:56"/>knoweth he getteth nothing by it, but vengeance. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in oppoſing againſt the Church of God, and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: whereas he knoweth he cannot hurt them, nay rather he doeth them good: he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Iob, and yet he knewe Iob by Gods own commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to be Gods ſeruant: he tempted Chriſt, whome hee knewe to be the Meſſias and Sauiour of mankind.</p>
               <p>The miſcheife of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill alſo is a great, as it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from him, and as it ſeazeth vpon ſome perſons: he brought Chriſt to death, Iob to beggerie: he worketh miſcheiuouſly by the witch to deſtroy the goods and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men both good and baddes he bringeth men into ſinne and keepeth them in it,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13820:57"/>and ſo worketh their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and damnation, which is the greateſt part of his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife, howſoeuer it is not ſo eaſily obſerued.</p>
               <p>As the deuil is thus mightie, malitious, and miſcheiuous, ſo vndoubtedly he beſtird him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with all his skil to afflict Chriſt, and he euen to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt he could doe, no doubt wrecked himſelf vpon Chriſt, to ſpoile him if it had bin poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: &amp; ſo doth he and wil do to all gods children: yea he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying an vniuerſall hatred to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind &amp; al Gods creatures, will worke what villanie he can vpon them: he carried the ſwine headlong into the ſea: he cauſed the man that was poſſeſſed to beat himſelf with ſtones, &amp;c. Here therefore we ſee the goodneſſe of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13820:57"/>vs, &amp; toward mankind in generall, who repreſſeth &amp; bridleth the deuill, and chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth him ſo as he cannot doe what he liſt: for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhould not keep our cattel from his hands, nor money in our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor any of our goods for our vſe: nay our bodies ſhould be ſure to be torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and worſe then that, if god ſhould lay the raines in his necke: all men therefore good and bad are to conſider Gods goodneſſe towardes them thus farre forth, that they are moderately preſerued by him in their outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates from the deuils tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</p>
               <p>It may be demanded how farre forth the deuill could and nowe did preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt in this place:<note place="margin">They comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, incloſe, and gape vpon me.</note>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:13820:58"/>or whether the deuils were the executioners of Gods wrath, now vpon our Sauiour Chriſt: whereto anſwer may be made thus; Firſt it ſeemeth that the inflicting of Gods wrath vpon the creature is Gods worke onely, and there is no creature that can poure Gods wrath vpon another; for the wrath of God beeing the curſe of the lawe to be inflicted vpon the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the law, for the breach of the lawe, whereby Gods iuſtice is violated, and this curſe, or this wrath of God beeing the effects of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, it is not conuenient to aſſigne the execution thereof to the deuill. For the deuil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe ſubiect to, and tormented with the ſenſe and feeling thereof, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13820:58"/>no ſuperiour power to torment the deuill, but God, he himſelfe muſt needs be the executioner of the deuils: and there beeing a kind of infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Gods wrath, ſo at the deuill thereby is ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, howe ſhall it be ſaid with reaſon, that he that is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnable to ſuſtaine it, ſhould inflict it, he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beare it himſelfe ſhould lay it vpon others? and as he that is hanged cannot be hangman; no more can the deuill that is tormented with Gods wrath, torment others therewithall. Therefore the Lord with his owne hand doeth immediately inflict his wrath vpon the creature, whether men or Angels: and as God had the helpe of no creature in the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13820:59"/>redemption, iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſanctification, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, no more hath he any helpe in the damnation of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the deuils were not Gods inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his wrath vpon Chriſt, and yet Chriſt ſuffered im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the deuils, as it is here recorded, for they tempt him, and terrifie him, they compaſſe him about, and incloſe him with temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, they gape vpon him with their mouthes as readie to deuoure him and teare him in peeces, that is, they vrge and enforce the wrath of God with all poſsible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and reaſon, aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to the vtmoſt of their skill. And it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13820:59"/>tempted Chriſt, and no doubt Chriſt could not ſuſtaine the vrging of the temptation without ſome ſorrowe and griefe and vexation of heart, as euery godly man hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, when he reſiſteth a temptation: for concluſion of this point, the deuils did not execute Gods wrath vpon Chriſt, but the deuils did te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt and terrifie Chriſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">I am like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter powred out, my bones diſſolued, &amp;c.</note>The effects that followed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the torture which Chriſt ſuſtained, proueth the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and extraordinarineſſe thereof, to omitte the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects which are ſet downe in the ſtory of the goſpel, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhould the diſſoluing of the facultie of ſenſe and motion proceeded in ſo much as that the bones beeing vntied
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13820:60"/>were ſeuered each from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? ſurely euen as Baltaſhar when he ſaw the hand writing had his ioynts, through the feeling of ſome diuine power that in iuſtice ſmote him for his ſinnes, looſed, ſo as his knees beate together, the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall facultie for a ſeaſon bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpended, euen ſo was it in Chriſt. Againe whence came the melting of the heart like waxe, the drying vp of the ſtrength like a potſheard, but from the intollerable heat of Gods firie wrath which nowe pearced our ſauiour Chriſt, and conſumed him as the fire that came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen conſumed the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice into aſhes: which was a tipe of this fire which thus dryed and ſcorched our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt and melted his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:13820:60"/>heart, as waxe melteth at the ſunne: How came it to paſſe that Chriſts tongue claue to his Iawes?<note place="margin">My tongue cleaueth to my Iawes.</note> was it immoderate drought that cauſed it? but then it ſhould haue bene ſaid: to the palate: but the prophet ſaith to the lawes: according to the latine phraſe <hi>vox fauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus haeret,</hi> Chriſt was not able to ſpeake, but his words were halfe words, words ſounding a farre of, faintly, his tongue faultred as it were in ſpeaking it may be that Chriſt was drie but that drought ſignified in the Goſpell when they gaue him viniger mingled with gal ſhould haue beene mentioned in the 16. verſe in due place when he ſuffered vpon the croſſe, and not here where the effects of an other torture are repeated, namely of that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13820:61"/>which imediately affected his ſoule, as hath beene ſaid; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all likelihood of reaſon ſome extraordinary tortures are here implyed which produce ſo ſtrang effects, and make ſuch deepe impreſſions in al the faculties of the ſoule, animall, vitall, naturall, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: whereby the parts of the body ſeruiceable to the ſoule for the execution of her faculties are forſaken.</p>
               <p>The vſe of this doctrine is to teach vs carefully to auoid ſinne which wrought ſuch ſtrange affectes in Chriſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying for ſinne, beeing god alſo: alas how ſhall wee vild wretches be able another day if it fall to our Lott for our ſinnes to ſuſtaine the leaſt hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh torment? it is no maruaile though the rich glutton in hel
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13820:61"/>crie out of his tong, &amp; though Baltaſhars knees knocke to gether, though Iudas hanged himſelfe, and Cayn blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and Saull fell vpon his ſword, ſeeing there are ſuch intollerable effectes followe the warth of God euen in the ſonne of God himſelfe as are here mentioned.<note place="margin">Thou haſt brought me into the duſt of death.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Here the prophet turneth his ſpeech vnto the Lord: &amp; whereas before he had made a narration of the might mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and miſcheefe of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies how they had afflicted him, by terour and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and how ſtraungelie this affliction tortured him, that it cauſed the faculties of the ſoule to intermit there functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in there proper parts of the bodie, now he maketh an apoſtrophe as it were
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13820:62"/>vnto the Lord, and telleth him, that it was he that had brought him to his death, for though his eſtate nowe was in all likelihood of reaſon ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recouerable and remedileſſe, beeing ſpilt like water vpon the ground, which cannot be gathered vp againe, yet all this ſorrowe did not kill him, but he changeth his ſpeech, and ſaith: thou haſt brought me into the duſt of death: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce two things may be obſerued: the one is, that God had a ſtroak in the death of Chriſt, not onely by permitting the Iewes to kill him, which ſhall be handled afterward in the 16. and 17. verſes, but by pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his wrath vpon him, which haſtened his death the ſooner, in ſo much as the hiſtorie in the goſpell ſaith,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13820:62"/>he was dead ſooner then the theeues who died the ſame death with him, as is likely: which haſtie death of Chriſts was cauſed no doubt by ſome inwarde cauſe, which was Gods wrath, that had wrought the former ſtrange effectes in Chriſt: that it may be properly ſaid that God killed Chriſt rather then the Iewes, though the Iewes alſo tortured his bodie, ſo as that in time he ſhould haue died. The other thing that we note here is, that all the might, malice, and miſcheife of the deuills, and the Iewes which was expreſt in the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing and tormenting of Chriſt, could not haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſt, except God had killed him. For Chriſt bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, could if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13820:63"/>him, and if the decree of god had not beene otherwiſe, haue retained his ſpirit, cured his wound, or deſtroyed his enemies that they ſhould not haue beene able to wound him: in regard whereof hee ſaith. Ioh. 10.18. that <hi>he had power to lay downe his life and to take it vp againe,</hi> and that his life was not wreſted out of his hand but ſeeing God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed it otherwiſe therefore Chriſt muſt needes die, and yet the principall crucifier of Chriſt (that I may ſo ſpeake generally) was God himſelfe, who beſides that he vſed the Iewes, and the Deuills as his inſtruments to murder Chriſt yet he retayneth in his owne handes one ſoueraigne tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the moſt fearefull wrath of God to bee inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13820:63"/>Chriſt our ſurety, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof the propet ſaith of Chriſt, thou haſt brought me into the duſt of death.</p>
               <p>Summarily (to ende the torments which immediatly tortured Chriſts ſoule) wee may here obſerue that Chriſt was thus afflicted as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed alreadie, both wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and neceſſarily: wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly in that he ſuffered the Deuills thus to aſſault him with terour and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: neceſſarily in that God had a hand in killing him, and bringing him to the graue which is deaths duſt: and indeed Chriſt did wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and yet neceſſarily ſuffer all that hee ſuffered: hence then two conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents followe immediately.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:13820:64"/>
               <p n="1">1 Chriſt infinite loue that was content and willing to ſuffer ſuch hardſhip for vs wretched caitifes: and.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That no leſſe then that which Chriſt ſuffered was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for our redemption &amp; reconcilation to God, ſeeing that he ſuffered all that he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered neceſſarily: for if it bee ſuppoſed that the leaſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt had beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough to haue appeaſed God towards vs, then it is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and vnneceſſary that Chriſt ſhould come into the duſt of death: ſhould haue ſuch ſtraung effectes in his bodie before his death; ſhould be ſubiect to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and temptations of the deuil: to the woundes and ſtripes of the Iewes: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was neceſſary that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13820:64"/>Chriſt ſhould ſuffer all theſe things and ſo enter into his glorie, therefore the leaſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of Chriſt was not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. This alſo might call into queſtion the lawe of God to his beloued ſonne in that hee would bring him to the duſt of death, if it were not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: and if it were neceſſarie that Chriſt ſhould die &amp; that by Gods owne hand (rather and more then by the Iewes woundes, and the Deuills worke) as is here noted, I would knowe what that hand of God was, if it was not the wrath of God working the former ſtraung effectes in Chriſts bodie: and if Chriſt muſt of neceſſity die, why muſt he not of neceſſitie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Gods wrath properly? ſhall we ſay Gods loue would
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13820:65"/>not ſuffer that? But Gods Iuſtice did require it: and Gods loue would ſuffer him to die: but neceſſitie vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a deſpenſation? What ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity I pray you? euen this perhaps that if Gods wrath had ſeazed vpon Chriſt, hee would haue bene forſaken of God: why? <hi>he was forſaken of God</hi> Pſal. 22.1. all comfort was ſecluded from him, and yet all grace was preſent with him: but it was impoſſible that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer gods wrath? wherefore impoſſible? becauſe he was God? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo it was impoſſible that he ſhould die, but poſſibility admitted his death: and why not Gods wrath? for neither the Godhead died nor ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gods wrath, but the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood only and the hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13820:65"/>vnion was neuer diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; there is no daunger of fearing any abſurdity to enſue vpon the ſuffering of Gods wrath rather then vpon the ſuffering of death: for deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, want of faith, loue, &amp;c. are not to be feared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The affliction that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſeazed vpon Chriſts bodie.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">V. 16.17, 18.</note>
                        <hi>16.</hi> For dogges haue compaſſed me; and the aſſembly of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed haue incloſed me, they pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my hands and my feet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>17</hi> I may tell all my bones, yet they behold and looke vpon me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>18</hi> They part my garments among them and caſt lottes vpon my veſture &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Theſe words containe that affliction which directly and immediately was inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13820:66"/>Chriſts bodie, which no doubt pierced the ſenſitiue part of the ſoule, which was inherent in the parts of the bodie wounded, for we ſee woundes in the parts of the bodie are ſenſible, and ſo very grieuous: the reaſon is; for that the obiect and the inſtrument of ſenſe are ioined togither without a medium, whereas there ought to be a competent diſtance, and a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient medium, which is called <hi>Cuticula.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here in the firſt place the perſons inflicting theſe bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly torments vpon Chriſt, are to be conſidered, who are called dogges, whereas the deuils in the former part of Chriſts torments were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Buls and Lyons: &amp; the compariſon hath in it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13820:66"/>conueniencie &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, for as it is an eaſier matter to encounter a dog, then a mightie madde Bull, &amp; a lyon, ſo the conflict which Chriſt had with the wicked, which were but a company of curre dogges, was nothing in compariſon of the combate he had with the deuill and his angels, whoſe malice, might, and miſcheife againſt Chriſt ſurpaſſed the villanie of the Iewes, as farre as the lyon rampeth and roareth more cruelly then the dogge bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: and yet Chriſt ſuffered more then that alſo, which was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of al miſery.</p>
               <p>The wicked in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are compared to dogges in reſpect of two properties which dogges haue, wherein wicked men are anſwerable to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13820:67"/>them: the one is churliſhnes the other is filthines: for the dogge will ſnarle at him that beateth him for his fault, yea though he be his maſter, Mat. 7.6. and he will alſo turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and eate the carrion which he hath vomited, 2. Pet. 2.22. which noteth out vnto vs two ſorts of wicked men: one is open perſecutors that reuile and perſecute them that ſmite them with holeſom reproofes, when they are faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: another is temporizing hypocrites, that hauing made a ſhewe of godlineſſe, as if they had vomited ſinne out of their ſoules, yet at length returne again, &amp; take vp their former ſinnes, which only for a time in hypocriſie they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke.</p>
               <p>Further this place warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth (and innumerable more)
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13820:67"/>that the aſſemble of wicked men that are temporizers or perſecutors may lawefully be called dogges, or a kennell of hounds: men now a daies that ſerue times, and perſecute the church take it in dudgin (as we ſay) that they ſhuld be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led dogs, or ſwine, or lyons, or beares, &amp;c. &amp; yet they haue all the properties of theſe brutiſh creatures, as if bruite beaſtes were metamorphized &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into men, as the heathen haue allegorized: of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. I would dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; whether is worſe to be a dog, or to be called a dog? may not a man call a dog a dogge? Wherfore if ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be dogs, I knowe no reaſon but they may be ſo called, eſpecially the h. ghoſt going before, whoſe example is our inſtruction in the ſame caſe: either therefore
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13820:68"/>lett ſuch men ceaſe to bee dogges, or if they ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue dogges let them be called dogges.</p>
               <p>Againe ſome take the prick whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are not prickt at all in the miniſters intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-althogh they are prickt in the Lords diſpoſition: for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the miniſter intendeth in his miniſterie that which neuer pearceth: &amp; ſometime God cauſeth that to pearce in his miniſterie that which hee neuer intendeth, yet it may be knowne that Pauls plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and Apollos watring is nothing except God giue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: There are men called by the names of beaſts, as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fox, hart, hare, hound, or ſo forth, and theſe men are ſome good ſome bad, as our owne experience may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13820:68"/>vs well enough: nowe ſometime it falleth out that the miniſter in his miniſterie is occaſioned by the ſcripture to vnfold the euill properties of wicked men in regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to beaſts as the lyons properties are prid and crueltie, the foxes craft and ſubteltie, the hearts fearefullnes, &amp;c. and it may fall out that ſome wicked man called lyon hath the lions prid and cruelty, ſome wicked man called fox hath the foxes craft and ſubteltie &amp;c. now if theſe men take themſelues either named or aymed at in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, where as it may be the miniſter neuer dreameth thereof; or if the miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch a thing, whence ſhould a man ſay this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth? without doubt either
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13820:69"/>groſſe folly, or an accuſing conſcience, or meere mallice, or brutiſh ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce bring me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into theſe ſurmiſes: howſoeuer it be gods word, it is a ſharpe two edged ſword; &amp; the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which to him perhaps is chance med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, ſometime ſhal wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him whome he neuer aimed at, or harden him, whome he neuer thought of: for the word of God is both a ſauour of life &amp; of death to ſeueral ſorts of perſons. Theſe are the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that afflicted Chriſt, let vs fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider what afflictions befel him: they crucifie him, &amp; mock him, they ſtrip him na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and diſpoile him of his garments: all which are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſufferings of Chriſt for our good: he was crucified, &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the moſt accurſed death of the croſſe, to deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:13820:69"/>the curſe of the law, Gal. 3.13, he was mockt to make vs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, he was robbed to make vs rich, &amp; was ſtript na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to couer our nakednes: al theſe benefits we haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all Chriſts ſufferings, though not each of them ſeuerally fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like ſuffering in Chriſt, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer allegorically thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">They pierced my hands and my feet, I may tell all my bones.</note>But one thing eſpecially is here to be conſidered concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the crucifying of Chriſt, in what ſenſe Chriſt beeing vpon the tree, &amp; there put to death, was accurſed: for expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, we are to know, that to die vpon a tree is not a thing indeede accurſed, either in nature or ciuill conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of it ſelfe. Nature doth not teach vs, that to hang vpon a tree is a thing accurſed, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be thruſt through with
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13820:70"/>a ſword, or to be preſt to death, or to be burnt, or ſo forth.</p>
               <p>Againe no poſitiue or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill lawes of any nation vnder heauen haue accurſed thoſe perſons that haue beene han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon a tree vntill their bodies haue died, indeed the death is ſomething more baſe and vilde then ſome other kind of death is, in reputation among ſome perſons, whence in our nation it ſeemeth that noble men haue ſome priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that way, that they die not as other ſorts of perſons die. And laſtly, the death of the tree hath no curſe in it ſelfe: we reade of diuers men that were godly men that died vpon the tree; as the peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarie that died with Chriſt, &amp; Chriſt himſelfe alſo: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13820:70"/>teacheth vs that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euery yeare: for many men betwixt their condemnation and execution haue beene deepely humbled for there ſinnes, and ſo haue died the true ſeruants of God: where fore the death of the croſſe (which Chriſt ſuffered) was not thus accurſed: how then was it accurſed? ſurely by the iudiciall and ceremoniall lawe of Moſes and not otherwiſe: that lawe which Moſes gaue from God the lawgiuer of the Iewes Deut 21.23. contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a prohibition with a reaſon annexed thereto: The prohibition is in theſe words: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer his bodie that is hanged vpon the tree to remaine all night vpon the tree:</hi> and this prohibition is a meare Iudiciall law of Moſes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13820:71"/>the which the people of the Iewes onely, were bound to obſerue; which lawe if the people of the Iewes had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated, they ſinned ſo againſt God, that the land was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with the ſinne, Deut. 21.23. The reaſon of that prohibition is in theſe words: <hi>For the curſe of God is on him that is hanged:</hi> and this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a meere ceremoniall lawe: (for it hath bin proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that neither by the lawe of nature, by ciuill or poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue lawe, or of it ſelfe, to be hanged vpon a tree is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;) it is therefore a meere ceremonie: but we know that Chriſt is the ſubſtance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ceremonie: wherefore the Lord foreſeeing that Chriſt ſhould die vpon a tree, &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tree ſuffer the curſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13820:71"/>of the lawe due vnto our ſins, as our ſuretie: therefore he ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pically figured out this curſe in the death of malefactours amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people of the Iews, that were ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tree: ſo that euery malefactor that was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Iews, was a type of Chriſt, and therfore was accurſed: not really (for it is want of charitie to think ſo) but ceremonially and typical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto vs Chriſt, who was truely and really ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed for vs: in that he ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned gods wrath which is the curſe of the lawe, which we ſhould haue ſuſtained: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing Chriſt was really accurſed as hath beene proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by this diſcourſe, therfore he vndoubtedly ſuffered gods wrath which is the curſe.<note place="margin">Yet they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold &amp; looke vpon me.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had nailed Chriſt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13820:72"/>to the croſſe and wrackt his ioynts ſo as that his bones might bee numbered they heape vpon him all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities they can: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt they behold &amp; look vpon him: alas it was a piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fight for one that had any manhood in him, to ſee a man nayled hands and feete with great nailes (as they muſt needes be ſeeing the hebrue word ſignifieth ſuch a pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, as was more like dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gig: or ſuch a pearcing as a lyon maketh with his clawes); to ſee the blood iſſue aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the woundes; to ſee his bodie ſtrecht ſo as that one ioynt was ſeuered from an other which is an extreame torture, for a bodily torment; and yet they behold and look vpon him without any pitty
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13820:72"/>at all; nay they mock and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid him as appeareth plaine in the hiſtorie of the Goſpell, &amp; when he would haue had a litle drinke to aſſwage his thirſt, they gaue him viniger mingled with gaul to increaſe his thirſt the more, gaull bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing biter of it ſelfe; all theſe ſhamefull outragies they offered to Chriſt nowe in dying; whence we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; not only the barbarous crueltie of theſe perſons, but further the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of him which is to grow one from degree to degree, till it come to an heigth and a fearefull exceſſe; theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons firſt contemned Chriſt a doctrine, depraued his life, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his death, now moſt cruelly murder him, and yet that doth not ſatisfie them,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13820:73"/>but they mock at him in the middeſt of his miſery: &amp; will not affoard him any eaſe at al: It is good to gainſtand ſinne at the firſt, leaſt if it get grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of vs at length it conquer and ſubdue vs: for the Lord ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time accuſtometh to puniſh one ſinne with another, and when men will not preuent ſmall ſinnes, they ſhall bee plunged into a ſea of fearefull impietie: as the Gentiles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when they knewe God they did not glorifie him as God, fell to Idolatrie and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that to ſinne againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and they in the ſeate of Antichriſt becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not the loue of the truth, therefore are giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſtrang deluſions to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue lies that they might bee damned. Rom. 3.2. Theſ. 2.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13820:73"/>when they had thus ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully handled Chriſt,<note place="margin">They part my garments and caſt lottes one my veſture.</note> they proceede to the deuiding of his garments (for they ſtript him of his cloathes when they crucified him) and here wee may obſerue diuers points worth our noting: for what ſhould be the reaſon that the holy Ghoſt ſhould thus care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expreſſe this practiſe of the ſouldiers in deuiding his garments &amp; caſting lottes for his veſture? no doubt this is ſome ſpeciall matter euen in this their practiſe, eſpecially ſeeing the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt alſo teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the ſame thing to be done by the ſoldiers: ſome allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the matter after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt (ſay they) are the ſcriptures: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Chriſt is his Church, the ſouldiers are heretiques:
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13820:74"/>For although the heretiques rend the ſcriptures with falſe expoſition &amp;c. yet they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſſolue the vnitie of the Church with there errours: This doctrine is true, but it is not intended in this place. It is a meere folly and dotage thus to abuſe the ſcriptures, though the allegorie be neuer ſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But we are to knowe that one reaſon why the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes expreſſe theſe things is for the verifying of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy: that the euent might declare the truth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy: other profitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations may hence be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſouldiers deale as theeues which haue gotten a bootie: they make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of robbing a man &amp; yet they make a ſcruple in deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:13820:74"/>the ſpoile: the ſoldiers make no bones to kill Chriſt, and rob him of his garments, yet they are curious in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding his apparrell amongſt them: for it is a right proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of an hypocrite to ſwallow a carnell, and to ſtrayne at a gnatt: to tith mint, cummin and anniſe ſeed, and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Iudgement, mercy, and faith: the ſoldiers neuer ſtrayne curteſy to iniury Chriſt, but they wil not iniury one another.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Againe the Holy Ghoſt ſeemeth to laie another fault among the ſoldiers that they caſt lottes for trifles, as if men ſhould card and dice for a coate: we neuer read in all the ſcriptures that lottes were vſed but in waighty matters, and it ſeemeth to be to take
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13820:75"/>the name of God in vaine, to ſport our ſelues with his immediate prouidence, as lots are.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Furthermore (if that bee not aſſented vnto) yet here is another thing flatly reproue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that by lottes (as it were cardes and dice) they would compaſſe parts of their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, getting away from another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by lott that which before was not theirs or wher to they had no title: for one of the ſouldiers muſt needes haue the whole coate (for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was without ſeame they would not cut it) and ſo the other three ſoldiers loſt their parts and he that gott the coat by lott, was a theefe to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three: for god hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed men to get there goodes by labour and lawfull
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13820:75"/>contractes not by carding and dicing and lotting, as the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers doe in this place.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Laſtly: it ſeemeth that Chriſts coate was worth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as alſo his garments for otherwiſe the ſouldiers would not haue regarded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus as they doe; and Chriſt was not ſo poore and begger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ſome begging fryers might peraduenture ſuppoſe him to be: neither is begging a ſtate of perfection, better then poſſeſſing &amp; vſing rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: we read that Paull had a cloake which he left at Troas, &amp; it is like he carried another with him, except we ſay he borowed one or went in his Ierkin: and though ſome mens riches are a ſnare vnto them, yet that is not in their riches, but in their corupt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13820:76"/>harts which are ſet vpon their riches: ſome mans pouertie alſo is a ſnare vnto him but that is in the wickednes of his owne heart alſo rather then in pouertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the requeſt and petition of the prophet repea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>19.</hi> But be thou farre of O Lord my ſtrength: haſten to helpe me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>20</hi> Deliuer my ſoule from the ſword, my deſolate ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of the dog.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>21</hi> Saue me from the Lyons mouth, and anſwer me in ſauing me from the hornes of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Hitherto the ſufferinges of Chriſt haue beene diſcuſſed: nowe it followeth to intreat more largely of the prayer that Chriſt maketh, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13820:76"/>whereof is here ſet downe by the prohet and it accordeth with the prayer which the Euangeliſt ſetteth downe Math 26. and Ioh. 12. <hi>Let this cup paſſe from me.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſaue me from this houre</hi> &amp;c. where this queſtion commeth to be ſcanned: what Chriſt praied for in this place, and in theſe two places of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes: or what Chriſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt: for the on of theſe include the other, and the ſupplication includeth the deprecation: for ſolution whereof: It muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be granted that he praieth either againſt a bodily death, or againſt Gods wrath; if it be ſaide, that he praied againſt a bodily death, then alſo it muſt needes be that he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either that it ſhould not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:13820:77"/>light vpon him, or that it ſhould not triumph ouer him; that is that the power of death ſhould not hinder him from riſing againe, that he ſhould not be held of the ſorrowes of death, Act. 2.24.</p>
               <p>Againe if it be ſaid that he prayed againſt Gods wrath, then one of theſe three things muſt of neceſſity be graunted: namely that he prayed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Either that Gods wrath ſhould not light vpon him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Or that it might depart from him beeing alreadie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Or that it might not ſwallowe him vp and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme him and eternally detayne him, and ſo cauſe him either to forfeite, or not to accompliſh our redep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:13820:77"/>
               <p>There beeing thus a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enumeration of parts, let vs proceed further and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire againſt which of al theſe he prayed.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore he prayed not againſt death that hee migh not taſt it: for God had determined that hee ſhould ſuffer death, and he knewe it very well it beeing figured in the ſacrifices of the old law, whereof he was the ſubſtance prophecyed by the prophets, ſignified to the diſciples by himſelfe. Mat. 16. and to ſay that he prayed againſt that, for which he knewe he came into the world were to make him pray againſt his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; againſt the expreſſe will of God reuealed in the word, which were blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to ſay of Chriſt in whoſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13820:78"/>mouth there was found no guile.</p>
               <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly alſo he praied not againſt Gods wrath, ſo as that it ſhould not light vpon him: for Matth. 20.22. he ſaith plainely, <hi>he muſt taſte of that cuppe:</hi> wherefore he did taſte it when he praied it might paſſe from him, Math. 26. &amp; the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is expreſt in this praier argueth ſo much: for in the place of Mat. 26.42. Chriſt ſaith thus, <hi>If this cuppe cannot paſſe from me, but that I muſt drinke it, thy wil be done:</hi> which wordes plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly import thus much: that whereas before the firſt time he praied this praier, he dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ſaid: let this cup paſſe from me, adding the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Math. 26.39. There was ſome oppoſition betwixt
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:13820:78"/>his naturall will and gods wil: nowe the ſecond time he praied, Chriſts will is wholly ſubmitted and ſubiected to Gods will, to drinke the cup prepared for him by God: as if Chriſt had ſaid, Father if it had beene poſſible, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thy will, I could wiſh that this cuppe of thy fierce wrath might paſſe away, ſo as that I might not taſt it, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it cannot paſſe till I haue drunke it. I ſubmit my ſelfe to thy will. And this praier in the ſame wordes he vttereth the third time: Math. 26.44. Where the changing of the wordes of the prayer in the verſe, 42. is to be carefully no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: which change is retained the third time he praied, v. 44. as if Chriſt had now vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed nature by grace; for there
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13820:79"/>was in Chriſt both nature &amp; grace, and that this ſecond praier was a correcting of the former: not as though his firſt praier were ſimply bad, but that nature ſeemed to carrie a greater ſway in the firſt, then in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; grace through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrected nature in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: other correcting I meane none: wherefore here Chriſt praied not that Gods wrath might not at al light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly therfore, &amp; for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, he praied againſt the other 3. parts of the diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mentioned before: againſt the dominion and continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gods wrath, and death. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the dominion of death and gods wrath he praied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, and that properly as our interceſſor, that neither himſelfe the head, nor we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the members, ſhould
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:13820:79"/>be ſubdued &amp; ouerwhelmed of them: but that himſelfe, and we by him might conquer &amp; vanquiſh them, &amp; triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them:<note place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note> and ſo he was heard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which he feared. One doubt will here ariſe, howe Chriſt could feare the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of death &amp; Gods wrath, for then Chriſt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted faith, &amp; doubted, which to ſay were blaſphemy: for anſwer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt feare and doubting. A man may feare that which he aſſuredly knoweth ſhall not befall him: Adam in Paradiſe might feare the wrath of god, and feare his apoſtacie &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from God, which was in him a vertue, &amp; yet ſurely A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had faith &amp; a perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods loue, &amp; aſſurance to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in grace, if he would: ſo likewiſe Chriſt might feare
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13820:80"/>leaſt the wrath of God might ouerwhelme him and vs, and yet be fully aſſured of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from it: Feare is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection: and no naturall affection is contrarie to grace, but ſubordinate to it: and Chriſt feared theſe things na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally; and furthermore the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Heb. 5.7. ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a fearefull and carefull declining and auoiding ſome imminent danger, by reaſon whereof the minde is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a great anxietie and ſollicitude, intending it ſelfe, with all the powers thereof to gainſtand the impendent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife: and thus Chriſt feared the dominion of death and gods wrath, and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe praied againſt it, he bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefully and reuerently bufied about the recouery of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13820:80"/>himſelfe, and the redeeming of vs from the power of death and the ſorrowes of hell: and becauſe praier is one excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meanes to furniſh a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian captaine againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie for obtaining the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: therefore Chriſt prayeth with ſtrong crying and teares vnto him that was able to ſaue him from death eternall, and was heard from that which he naturally feared, or rather from that, for declining whereof he was reuerently accumbred: nature working in him feare of it, and grace ſtirring vp praier againſt it: and there is no abſurditie to ſay, that Chriſt praied againſt that which he certainely and fully knewe ſhould neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall his Diſciples.</p>
               <p>And as Chriſt praied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13820:81"/>the dominion of death and gods wrath, ſo he praied alſo that the wrath of God might not ſtay longer vpon him, he beeing now alreadie tormented therewithall, &amp; ſo he ſaith, <hi>let it paſſe from me: ſaue me from this houre.</hi> For further explication whereof conſider 3. propoſitions or axioms fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Chriſt ſuſtaining the ful wrath of God in his ſoule, was wholly buſied in his whole ſoule, and all the faculties thereof in apprehending, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and bearing it, ſo as the ſoule &amp; faculties thereof were diſtracted from all their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, &amp; wholly applied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: as appeareth by the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge intermitting of the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſoule in the parts of the body, mentioned, v. 14.15.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:13820:81"/>
               <p n="2">2 We muſt diſtinguiſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; naturall infirmities fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin and ſinful infirmities: it is a naturall infirmitie for a man to ſleepe and be wearie, and ſo alſo ſuſtaining Gods wrath, to deſire to be releaſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it: but it is no ſinne at all.</p>
               <p n="3">3 We muſt knowe that Chriſt as he was man was ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of ſome things, as namely of the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mar. 13.32. for ſome ignorance is no ſinne: as for a miniſter to be ignorant of the manuarie trades: for a man to be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t where hel is, of the orders of angels. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now for applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe three axiomes: ſure it is that when Chriſt praied, he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without the leaſt ſpotte of ſinne: and either of theſe axiomes rehearſed will iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13820:82"/>Chriſt praier from the leaſt ſuſpition of ſinne: as it is thought.</p>
               <p>The firſt axiome iuſtifieth a certaine obliuion or forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in Chriſt, when all the faculties of the ſoule were interrupted through the ſenſe of Gods wrath: and wholly ſeazed with the intollerable paine thereof: this I dare not peremptorily ſay, euery way to be good and ſound, neither doe I reprooue it: onely thus much, it may ſeeme to be a fault for a man to forget when the ought to remember; and to ſay that Chriſt had nowe a holy forgetfulneſſe, when he ſhould moſt of all remember, euen when he was to make the vp-ſhotte (that I may ſo ſpeake) of our redemption, is not preſently without further
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13820:82"/>inquiſition to be admitted.</p>
               <p>In regard of the ſecond of theſe axiomes it may be more probably anſwered, that Chriſt ſuſtaining the wrath of God, and hauing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a man in him, which deſired releife fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo extreame torment (which is a naturall ſinleſſe worke) ſaid to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Let this cup paſſe, ſaue me from this houre, &amp;c.</hi> and in the very ſelfe ſame moment of time that nature deſireth, grace ſeaſoneth and qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nature, ſaying, <hi>Not my</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>will, but thy will be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:</hi> therefore came I into this houre. So here there is firſt a difference betwixt nature and grace; then a ſubordinating of nature to grace: alſo it may be a correcting of nature by grace, not as if nature were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13820:83"/>ſimply but a leſſe good: for it is good tor the creature to preſerue it ſelfe: it is better to obey gods wil by ſuffering according to his wil: eſpecially conſidering the coincidence of nature &amp; grace in the ſame time &amp; praier: for nature ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the requeſt, grace addeth the conditions.</p>
               <p>Nature ſaith thus:</p>
               <q>Father let this cuppe paſſe from me: ſaue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this houre.</q>
               <p>Grace ſaith:</p>
               <q>If it be poſſible: &amp; not my wil be done, but thine; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore came I into this houre</q>
               <p>In regard of the third axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om aforeſaid, it is thus anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that as Chriſt was ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the day of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out errour it may ſeeme, we may ſay he was ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:13820:83"/>time how long or how oft he ſhuld ſuffer the wrath of god: and ſo beeing vnder the hand of God, &amp; not knowing what ſpace of time god in his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting decree had ſet downe for enduring it, or how oft it ſhould make incurſion vpon him; he praied, <hi>Let it paſſe, &amp;c.</hi> that is, let it depart from me, I hauing now ſuſtained it; or let it not ſeaze vpon me againe, I hauing already ſuffered it; ſure it is, that Chriſt did vndergoe gods wrath a competent time, and diuers times, as Ioh. 12. Once Gods wrath like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning did flaſh vpon his face; alſo Math. 26. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time gods wrath moſt furiouſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted him, which wrought in him that ſtrange agonie &amp; ſweat: laſtly, hanging vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, when he cried out,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:13820:84"/>
                  <hi>My God, my God; why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> &amp; this third aſſault was the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plement of all his woes, for whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Garden an angell comforted, and ſo God had not cleane forſaken him, now God vtterly withdrewe from him all comfort; and ſo there was nothing but wrath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring him &amp; praying vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him without all mercy and comfort: but exqueſitely to determine howe oft, or how long at any time Gods wrath was vpon Chriſt, ſeeing the ſcripture hath not expreſt it, is meere curioſitie; and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man obiect that Chriſt prayed againſt Gods will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in praying thus; it is anſwered that he praied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods ſecret will it may be and that is no ſinne; and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13820:84"/>his prayer had conditions, &amp; ſo it was not againſt gods wil; It is no ſinne for the ſonne to pray for the life of his father, which ſhall ſhortly die, hee praying co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditionally. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to end all this diſcourſe of Chriſts prayer; it is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable as we ſee, in diuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects by ſaying either he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatt through the interrupting of the ſoule; or that nature corrected with grace made this requeſt; or that he prayed through ignorance, contrary to Gods ſecret will condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
               <p>Theſe things beeing thus diſcourſed the meaning of theſe wordes in the pſalme is very eaſie; as if the prophet ſhould haue ſaid more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without allegory thus all the powers of darkenes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:13820:85"/>now rage againſt mee, (the dogge the lyon the vnicorne the ſword) the Iewes, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (which is the ramping &amp; roaring lyon:) thy wrath and the curſe of the lawe: nowe father I doe not deſire that I may not incounter with them but that I may not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by them, ſaue me from the dominion of death &amp; thy wrath (from the power of the dogge, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyons mouth, from the hornes of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes) lette the Iewes (the dogges) crucifie and kill mee, let the Deuill and his angels (the lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vnicornes) tempt and terrifie me: let thy wrath and the curſe of the lawe (the ſword) ſeeing it muſt needes torture me: but yet father ſaue me, &amp; by me thy whole Church from periſhing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13820:85"/>thy wrath: Yea fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if I nowe haue ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thy wrath long enough and often enough (as that is hidden from me, as is the day of iudgement) releaſe me from it: but if it muſt needes ſtill reſt vpon me, I am content to beare it ſtill patiently, and that for the full and perfect redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Church.</p>
               <p>From theſe wordes para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtically thus expounded may ariſe a doubt:<note place="margin">V. 20. Deliuer my ſoule from the ſword.</note> why Gods wrath is called a ſword, or howe that expoſition is iuſtifiable: for ſatisfying wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the place, Zachar. 3.7. <hi>Ariſe o ſword, and ſmite the ſheapheard,</hi> which place is applyed by the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, Math. 26.31. to the death of Chriſt, alſo conſider
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:13820:86"/>the phraſe: the prophet pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that <hi>his ſoule may be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſword:</hi> his ſoule doth not ſignifie his life, but his very ſoule indeede the fountaine of life: for Chriſt did not pray againſt death that he might not taſt it: but that his ſoule might not be ſwallowed vp of death: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this muſt needes be the meaning of the place: let not thy wrath ouerwhelme my ſoule: for we cannot ſay pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly let not death ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme my ſoule, but let not death ouerwhelme my bodie. The ſoule dieth not but the bodie onely.</p>
               <p>Summarily then to end; this is not the meaning of the wordes: deliuer my life from death: <hi>Supra probutum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor this; deliuer my ſoule
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13820:86"/>from death, for the ſoule can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die, it is immortall.</p>
               <p>Nor this: deliuer my bodie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graue: for it is abſurd and impertinent to this place.</p>
               <p>Therefore this is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: deliuer my ſoule from thy wrath <hi>(my ſoule from the ſword)</hi> but the ſword did ſmit the ſhepheard: <hi>ergo</hi> Gods wrath did torture his ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deſolate (ſoule.)</note>The meaning of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet <hi>(deſolate)</hi> is expreſt v. 1. for Chriſts ſoule was deſolate, becauſe God had nowe forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, and neither himſelfe, man or angell or any creature did comfort him but all had forſaken him.. v. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">My ſtrength</note>Although Chriſt was deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of all comfort, yet he had ſtrength and grace ſufficient to beare whatſoeuer was inflicted vpon him by God
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:13820:87"/>as our ſuretie. And therefore neuertheleſſe he intitleth god his ſtrength, though he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth that God had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, and did not heare when he roared. verſ. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The promiſe of Thankefulneſſe: and firſt of Chriſts Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 22, 23, 24, 25.</note>22 I will declare thy name vnto my brethren: in the midſt of the congregation will I praiſe thee, (ſaying.)</p>
                     <p>23 Praiſe the Lord ye that feare him, magnifie ye him all the ſeed of Iacob, and feare yee him all the ſeed of Iſrael.</p>
                     <p>24 For he hath not deſpiſed nor abhorred the affliction of the poore: nether hath he hid his face from him, but when he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him he heard.</p>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:13820:87"/>
                     <p>25 My praiſe ſhall be of thee in the great congregatione my vowes will I performe before them that feare him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The Prophet hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet down the ſacrifice and interceſſion of Chriſt both in the torments which he ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned partly in his ſoule direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and from God himſelfe, partly in his body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iews that murthered him, as alſo in the vehement praier which he made, partly for himſelfe, and partly for vs, ſeeing the fruite thereof wholly redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto vs: now he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the prophecy &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt: and firſt the prophetical office of Chriſt is expreſt in theſe foure verſes.<note place="margin">Verſ. 22. I wil declare thy name vnto my brethren.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The principall worke of Chriſts prophecy is to declare
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:13820:88"/>Gods name, that is, his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent attributes, and his whole wil vnto his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iews, and ſo to the whole Church, for ſo this place is brought, Heb. 2.12. to prooue the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie of Chriſt: whence we conſider that Chriſt is deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God the father for the onely Prophet, Doctour, and teacher of the Church, he is the great Biſhop of our ſoules: God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to heare him: and he is the onely law-giuer that is able to ſaue and deſtroy: which is thus to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that he alone hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed his fathers will to the Church by the miniſterie of the prophets in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by his own, &amp; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles miniſterie in the new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, who ſpake as the H.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:13820:88"/>ghoſt directed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for Chriſt Ieſus hath in his breſt hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge, who is therefore called the wiſdome of God: and therefore we are not to adde to, or detract any thing from the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word of god, or to alter any whitte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which whoſoeuer preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to doe, derogateth from the propheticall office of Chriſt: the ſcriptures indeede may be expounded, but they muſt not be altered, augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or diminiſhed.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo followeth it by due proportion: that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Paſtors of the Church, who ſtand vp in Chriſts ſtead (he being aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp on high, and hauing giuen gifts vnto men) are to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and publiſh Gods will
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:13820:89"/>ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly reuealed by Chriſt in the Prophets and Apoſtles writings) to the people of God for their conuerſion &amp; ſaluation. Finally alſo by like analogie Chriſtians muſt without feare or ſhame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and profeſſe the truth of Gods word, not onely before the friends of the Church, &amp; thoſe ſpecially ouer whome they haue charge, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the enemies of the Church being called and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereunto.</p>
               <p>This is the principal work of Chriſts prophecie to teach the Church: nowe the effects thereof follow, which are the praiſe of God, &amp; the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of mens ſoules: which are ſubordinate each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for by the conuerſion of mens ſoules God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:13820:89"/>
               <p>The firſt effect of Chriſts propheticall office,<note place="margin">V. 25. Let the ſeed of Iacob &amp; Iſrael, feare, praiſe, and magnifie god.</note> and ſo of the miniſtery of the prophets, Apoſtles, and Paſtors of the church, is the conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mens ſoules: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called the gathering togither of the Saints, the edification of the bodie of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond effect of the Prophecie of Chriſt,<note place="margin">V. 22. In the middes of the congregation I will praiſe thee.</note> &amp; ſo of the miniſterie, is the praiſe of God, for therefore muſt miniſters preach &amp; teach that God may be glorified in the conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoules: thus Chriſt ſaith, I honour my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and again, I haue glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee on the earth: Where the miniſters, Paſtors, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Church are to learne in their functions to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:13820:90"/>ayme at theſe endes, that they may ſaue ſoules which is a great point of wiſdome, and gloryfie God which is the end of all things; where thoſe paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours are reproueable that ſeeke rather to wine their own praiſe by inkhorne lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by darkning and obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their preachings with the cloudes of phyloſophy &amp; the tongues, drawing as it were a vale before Chriſt crucyfied, and couering Moſes face with a ſcarfe; that men ſhould not with open face ſee the glory of God, then the praſe of god, and the conuerſion of mens ſoules, who are rather by this kind of preaching ſtill kept in the dungeon of ignorance and palpable darkenes that the day ſtarre Ieſus Chriſt cannot ariſe in their hartes;
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:13820:90"/>ſo that this kind of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is rather to put out, then to open the eies of the blind.</p>
               <p>Hitherto the prohet hath declared the propheticall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt in reuealing Gods will to the Church with the two effectes thereof, the conuerſion of mens ſoules and the glory of God (for the hardening of the wicked is no proper effect;) now the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet rendereth a reaſon of Chriſts propheticall office, wherefore he will reueale his fathers will to his Church; or wherefore the Church ought to praiſe God beeing conuerted becauſe that when Ieſus Chriſt beeing poore and in great humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wrath of God for the redemption of the Church
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:13820:91"/>called vnto his father, hee heard:<note place="margin">V. 24. He hath not deſpiſed the affliction of the poore: but heard his prayer.</note> and did not abhorre or deſpiſe his affliction, but with a pitifull eie regarded him and at length when hee had ſatisfyed gods iuſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him.</p>
               <p>Hence then we may learne two inſtructions.</p>
               <p>Firſt that the propheticall office of Chriſt is a fruit of his preiſthood, of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, ſacrifice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion: for if Chriſt had not died for vs, he had neuer reuealed his fathers will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: according as the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſte (Eph. 4.) doth reaſon Chriſt aſcended vp on high and led captiuitie captiue, and gaue gifts vnto men: but before hee aſcended hee diſcended and ſuffered death
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:13820:91"/>for vs.</p>
               <p>Secondly hence wee muſt learne euerlaſtingly to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all our good: for without it we had ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in blindnes &amp; ignorance without the knowledge of Gods word, and ſo we had groped in the palpable darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Aegipt: for the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall office of Chriſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reuealeth vnto vs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Chriſt which is the principall worke of his preiſthood, ſo that Chriſts ſacrifice is the halfe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his prophecy the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the lawe alſo through Chriſt prophecy is reſtored vnto vs ſound and perfect which through the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:13820:92"/>of Adam was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defaced, and the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lawe is qualified alſo by the conditions of the goſpell, that the Lord doth not nowe require perfect obedience in quantity, but in quality: and ſo through the redemption of Chriſt. The Goſpell is wholly reuealed, a matter altogether vnknowne to man by nature, and the law is reſtored, and qualified and made poſſible to the penitent and beleeuers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He heard whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he called.</note>Here a queſtion may bee made how God heard Chriſt when he praied: ſeeing in the firſt and ſecond verſes it is ſaid that god heard not: that doubt is anſwered before in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint: &amp; therefore it is neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe here to repeate it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:13820:92"/>
               <p>In this 25. verſe there are two phraſes to be obſerued:<note place="margin">Verſ. 25. My praiſe ſhal be of thee in the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</note> firſt what ſhould be meant by the great congregation: it ſeemeth that the Prophet hath reference to that which ſhould bee practiſed by Chriſt in his propheticall office: we reade in the booke of the Lawe, Deuteronom. 16. that all the males were commaunded to come vp to Ieruſalem thrice in the yeare, nowe that was no doubt a great congregation when all the males came thither to worſhippe: nowe there is an expreſſe place in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt, Iohn, 7.37. that Chriſt preached and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in the laſt and great day of the feaſt of Tabernacles, which was one of thoſe three great aſſemblies: and
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:13820:93"/>ſo that place of Iohn and this of the prophet are paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell in ſence: A ſecond phraſe doubtfull is: what is meant by Chriſtes vowes?<note place="margin">My vowes will I performe.</note> In the old teſtament vowes were of ſuch matters and of ſuch a condition as that before they were made, they were in a mans power, but after they were vowed they became ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, Eccleſ. 5.3.4. Act. 5.4 probably therefore it may be ſaid that Chriſts vowes were that voluntary ſubmiſſion of Chriſt to become our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, our prophet and king and prieſt, which was moſt free &amp; willing and vncompel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in him. Ioh. 10.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of Chriſts kingdome: or kingly office: and his ſubiects.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">26.27.28.29.30.31.</note>26 The poore ſhall eate &amp; be
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:13820:93"/>ſatisfyed, they that ſeeke after the Lord ſhall praiſe him, your ſoule ſhall liue for euer.</p>
                     <p>27 All the ends of the world ſhall remember themſelues and turne to the Lord, all the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of the nations ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe before thee, 28.</p>
                     <p>28 For the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is the lords &amp; he ruleth among the nations.</p>
                     <p>29 All they that be fatte in the earth ſhall eate and worſhip: all they that goe downe into the duſt ſhall bow befere him: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that cannot quicken his owne ſoule.</p>
                     <p>30 There ſeedd, ſhall ſerue him, it ſhall be counted to him foreuer.</p>
                     <p>31 They ſhall come &amp; ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his righteouſnes: becauſe he hath done it for a people to be borne.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In the kingdome of Chriſt
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:13820:94"/>the ſubiects are firſt to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered who are firſt deſcribed by two properties: which are indeed Properties euery way, wherein the wicked haue no part nor portion at all: which are theſe following.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Humiliation 2 faith 3 peace of conſcience 4 deſire of increaſe of grace 5 Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God 6 life euerlaſting: of each of them ſomething.</p>
               <p>Humiliation or contrition or ſorrowe for ſinnes is the firſt grace that appeareth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly in the ſoule of a Godly man, this is the ſacrifice that is well pleaſing in gods ſight;<note place="margin">v. 26 The poore.</note> &amp; the Lord hath promiſed to dwell with the man that hath a broken and contrite heart; and bleſſednes is promiſed by Chriſt to them that are poore in ſpirit; and Chriſt
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:13820:94"/>inuiteth all thoſe that are wery and laden with their ſinnes to come to him for refreſhing; and he came to call ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentance, whoſe hearts melt at the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſinnes whereby they offend a God that is moſt mercifull and iuſt.</p>
               <p>Faith is the ſecond grace which followeth humiliaton, the property whereof is to eate Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Shall eate.</note> to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and apply the ſacrifice of Chriſt particularly to it ſelfe: for faith is not a vaſt &amp; indiſtinct apprehenſion of Chriſt, or a confuſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite conceipt of Gods mercy to the world: but a diſtinct appropriating &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of gods mercie and Chriſts merit to my ſelf, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing in ſome meaſure, &amp; bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that Chriſt hath
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:13820:95"/>nayled, crucified, and buried my ſinnes to his croſſe, and in his graue, and to doe this is al the difficultie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">And be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note>Third property is ioy and peace and quietnes or conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when a man is aſſured of the pardon of his ſinnes through faith, a man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that God loueth him, and doth accept of his perſon, and watcheth ouer him to doe him good, hee knoweth that he is freed from death, and damnation through the redemption of Chriſt, that life euerlaſting, appertaineth to him, vnder hope whereof he reioyceth yea in the midſt of affliction, though ſomtime this peace bee diſturbed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſome sins wherin to the children of God fall through temptation: this is termed here
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:13820:95"/>
                  <hi>ſatisfying,</hi> not for that a man that hath it, neuer deſireth grace more: but becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world can ſatisfie him til he haue comfort in the aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his ſins pardoned, when a man is once through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbled; or becauſe a man neuer is barren and drie, and cleane void of grace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort after, that once hath it.</p>
               <p>Fourth propertie is deſire of increaſe of grace,<note place="margin">Seeke after the Lord.</note> which is obtained by ſeeking the Lord where and howe he is to be found, that is, in the word and the meanes of grace: for he that wanteth grace can neuer deſire it, onely he that hath it, and hath felt the ſweetnes of it longeth for it ſtill, like vnto the man that finding the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hid in the field, and the pearle, neuer reſteth till he get
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:13820:96"/>both: by this alſo a man may knowe the trueth of grace in his ſoule: for he that neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the word, neuer atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon inſtruction, nor watcheth to praier, that man wanteth grace: for the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly couetouſneſſe and dropſie of grace is inſatiable: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church is ſicke of loue vnto the Lord Ieſus Chriſt in the Canticles.</p>
               <p>A fifth propertie is the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a godly life according to gods commaundements,<note place="margin">Shall praiſe him.</note> with a conſtant profeſſion &amp; confeſſion of the trueth to the praiſe of God, that others may ſee our good works, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God alſo. Alſo a thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart whereby a man in himſelfe bleſſeth God for all his goodnes, ſaying with the Prophet, <hi>All that is within me
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:13820:96"/>praiſe his holy name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euerlaſting life is the laſt propertie,<note place="margin">Your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall liue for euer</note> which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of all the former: and which is the complement of our happineſſe and felicitie.</p>
               <p>After the deſcription of the ſubiects of Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by their properties fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſeuerall ſorts of them: Gentiles as wel as Iews, poore as well as rich: malefactors condemned to die, as well as guiltlesse perſons; the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as well as the parents. Yea and the kingdome of Chriſt conſiſteth of all other ſortes of perſons that may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed: as bond and free, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; woman, maſter and ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp;c. Generally hence may be noted two inſtructions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, wherefore the church is called Catholike; becauſe it
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:13820:97"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of al ſorts of perſons, it is in al places: it is at al times. v. 27.29.30, 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">V. 29. All that be fatt all that goe downe into the pitt.</note>Secondly that grace is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall no ſort or eſtate of men excluded form Chriſts kingdom: ethe poore haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt to grace and Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as the rich, the gentill aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as the Iewe, women aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as men: yet wee muſt knowe that the note of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality muſt not be ſtretcht to euery particular man, but to euery eſtate and condition of man. For it is more then groſſe abſurdity to ſay that all and euery particular rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and poore man ſhall bee a member of Chriſt, ſhall eate and worſhip, that is beleeue and ſerue God: wherefore this doctrine ſerueth to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh firſt the welthie and fatt
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:13820:97"/>men of the earth not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and deſpiſe the poore, and the leane &amp; needie ſoule: and the poore not to enuie the rich, and malice the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie: but both to ſerue togither in their places, and to preſerue the communion of ſaints mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, remembering the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles rule, Iam. 1.9.10. that the poore is exalted, and the rich is made lowe in Ieſus Chriſt: that though the rich be the poore mans maſters, yet he is Chriſts ſeruant: and though the poore man be the rich mans ſlaue, yet he is the ſonne of God, and fellow heire with him, and with Chriſt of the kingdome of grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Beſides theſe generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, certaine particular obſeruations also are here to be noted which followe.</p>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:13820:98"/>
               <p>The Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Verſ 27. The ends of the world. The kindreds of the nations.</note> that the Gentiles ſhal become ſubiects to Chriſts kingdome: which prophecie we ſee verified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs at this day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we are to be ſtirred vp to glorifie the mercie &amp; truth of God, who hath caſt off his owne people, and receiued vs, that were wilde branches of the wilde oliue, that were ſtrangers and aliants from the common wealth of Iſrael: without God in the world: which muſt alſo teach vs not to be hie minded, but to feare, and looke to our ſelues that we ſtand faſt.</p>
               <p>Againe, the conuerſion of the Gentiles is here noted out vnto vs in the 3. parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p n="1">1 They ſhall remember themſelues,<note place="margin">Shall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> that is, their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:13820:98"/>and accurſed eſtate: they ſhall take notice of it by the powerfull preaching of the Goſpell: humiliation.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Turne to the Lord.</note>2 They ſhall turne to the lord: forſaking their falſe way of Idolatry and other ſinnes and turning their feet into the truth, &amp; walking in obedience of Gods lawes: obedience.</p>
               <p n="3">3 They ſhall worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,<note place="margin">Worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</note> by partaking al the meanes of ſaluation, as the word, prayer, ſacraments. &amp;c. publikely and priuately as good chriſtians: adoration.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Kingdome i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lords.</note>Nowe becauſe this may ſeeme a very ſtaunge thing to the Iewes that the gentiles ſhould be admitted into the fellowſhip of the Church, the partition wall beeing broken downe &amp; one people beeing made of two: the prophet ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:13820:99"/>a reaſon hereof, desig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out the principall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of this conuerſion of the gentiles and the meanes? the workman is the Lord: who is able to raiſe vp children vnto Abraham euen of the ſtones: who is able to put life into the dead bones in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: and the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God will effect and bring to paſſe this great worke is his rule and dominion which hee exerciſeth among the nations,<note place="margin">He ruleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> by his word and ſpirit which breatheth where it liſteth: whence that doctrine may be noted that was handled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. v. 3. that conuerſion is Gods worke.</p>
               <p>Furthermore not only we that now liue,<note place="margin">Verſ 10. Their ſeed ſhal ſerue him, &amp;c.</note> but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſeed &amp; poſterty that ſhal ſucceed vs in time to come ſhall ſerue
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:13820:99"/>the Lord: for the Couenant of grace ſtretcheth not onely to vs, but to our ſeede alſo: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the thouſand generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on of them that loue God, doth the Lord promiſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and the promiſe is made to vs, and our children, and to all that are afarre off, euen to as many as the Lord our God ſhal cal: which giueth vs hope for our children as well as for our ſelues, yea for our infants that die before yeares.</p>
               <p>Yea and here is one thing more,<note place="margin">They ſhall be counted to him for euer.</note> wherein it ſeemeth we haue a priuiledge beyonde the Iewes, that the Church of God ſhall abide among the Gentiles to the worlds ende: not as though no particular Church ſhall be caſt off, for we ſee that otherwiſe, but that the Church ſhall not vtterly
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:13820:100"/>faile among the gentiles for ouer, as it did among the Iews; for although the church of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus; Coloſſa; Gallatia &amp;c. fayled, yet from the time of calling the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles hitherto there hath bin ſome church of the gentiles. And although the Iewes were cut of and we grafted in; yet wee ſhall not be cut of and they grafted in, but we ſhal remaine, and they ſhall be grafted to vs and both of vs ſtand and growe vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: and as they were a meanes to bring vs into the Church, ſo we againe ſhall be a meanes to bring them vnto the fellowſhip of the goſpell (as it were a recompence vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 31 They ſhall declare his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>Againe the church of the gentiles beeing gathered ſhall performe one principall office
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:13820:100"/>which is, beeing come home into the boſome of Chriſt, by effectuall vocation and true faith, ſhal declare the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of Chriſt God-man, that righteouſneſſe which he hath wrought for vs, in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and obeying the lawe: manfully auouching it againſt the Turkes and Papiſts that denie imputatiue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and mocke at a crucified Chriſt: which muſt cheere vs vp in this ſpirituall conflict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that man of ſinne, that we faile not in defence of Gods righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>If any man liſt to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by righteouſneſſe that which God exerciſed in the whole worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhewing himſelfe moſt righteous therein, he may for me.</p>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:13820:101"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He hath wrought it for a people to be borne.</note>The foreſaid worke of the church of the Gentiles in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouching Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt be performed eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a people that is not yet borne by ſpirituall regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to a people vnbaptized: for we are to labour by all poſſible means to bring home the Iewes and the Turkes, and all other barbarous nations where we traffique, to the knowledge and loue of the trueth: that they may partake in this righteouſneſſe which Chriſt hath wrought for as many of them as appertaine to his election.</p>
               <p>If any man thinke better to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a people to be borne, ſuch as are not borne by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall generation, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that it is our dutie to teach our children and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:13820:101"/>eſpecially the article of iuſtification by faith onely, leaſt the ſubtill and crafty Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites the ſupporters and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of popery wreſt it from vs, who labor to perſwade the meritt of good workes and ſo to ſhoulder the Lord Ieſus Chriſt his righteouſnes out of dores.</p>
               <p>Thus the kingdome of Chriſt alſo is deſcribed.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:102"/>
            <head>The Author doth intreat the gentle reader in the behalfe of the Printer, to pardon and to correct theſe faults ouerſeene in printing.</head>
            <p>Page, 19 lin 23. for p iuately, read primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. p. 20 l 2. for practiſe, read parts. p. 21. l. 23. for men, more p 32 l. 23. for this, thus p. 34. A I ſalme p 35 of Dauid theſe two clauſes are wanting on the margents of theſe two pages. p. 45. l. 9. for in very, in a very p. 47. l 2 and, is ſupe fluous. p. 62. l 9. For faith, fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re. p. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 18. the note of interrogation is ſo perfluous. p 66. l 13. for Scripture, ſcepter. p 68. 1 9 for, and, read of the. p. 69. l. 22. for conie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, confutation. p. 78 l 13. for world of begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning read worlds beginning. p 83. l 1. for woman, worme. p. 91. l. 24. are denied &amp; are ſuperfluous p. 92. l. 1. for that, yet p.121. l 6. for law. loue. p. 128. l. 15. for yet, that. p. 137. l. 16 for him read ſinne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13820:102"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
